music
music
problem
문제
ened
ened
was
was
steals
steals
circle
circle
There is something important so he can't come
有重要的事情所以他沒辦法來
Entrust me to help him host
委託我來幫他主持
So I'm a layman on the subject of today's phenomenon
所以我對今天的現象的主題比較外行
If you say something wrong, please don't take effect
如果說錯什麼請各位不要見效
Everyone knows that the feast of knowledge is very important to this feast
各位都知道知識饗宴是本宴非常重要的
An important activity promoted by popular science knowledge
一個科普知識推動的重要活動
I just saw an official document today
我今天才看到一個公文
The seventh feast of knowledge will gather and mature after the lecture
第七本知識饗宴在講完之後都會集結成熟
The seventh is also about to run
第七本也快要運行了
The first six are easily available at bookstores
前六本很容易就可以在書店
or where to find
或什麼地方找到
Welcome to go and have a look
歡迎各位去找來看一看
All we invite are inside and outside the courtyard
我們邀請的都是院內外
very good experts
非常出色的專家學者
Come and talk to us about the latest scientific developments
來跟大家談談最新的科學發展
we are very happy to have you today
我們今天非常高興請到
Institute of Atomic and Molecular Research, Academia Sinica
中央研究院原子分子研究所
The current director, Dr. Zhou Meiyin
現任的所長周美寅博士
Dr. Zhou came back from the United States in January this year
周博士是今年1月才從美國回來
Join Academia Sinica
加入中央研究院
Institute of Atomic and Molecular Sciences
擔任原子分子科學研究所
Everyone knows that the Fate Institute is a very good fault of the Academia Sinica
各位知道緣分所是中央研究院非常出色的一個錯
Then it has a high status in the world
那麼在國際上有很高的地位
So today he is going to talk about the latest development of nanomaterials
那麼他今天是要來談奈米材料的最新發展
Nano?
奈米呢
I only gradually heard the name in the late 1990s
我是在1990年代後期才逐漸聽到這個名字
I remember once in the Legislative Yuan there was a legislator
記得有一次在立法院有一位立法委員
The nanometer plan sent by the National Science Council seems to be worth one billion
對國科會送上來的奈米的計畫好像要舉十億
He said that this Taiwanese Penglai rice can't finish it
他說這個台灣澎萊米都吃不完
How much do you spend on Nano
你們還花什麼多錢人家奈米
so he is like me
所以他跟我一樣
It was the first time I came into contact with nano
在當時都第一次接觸到奈米
Nano NSA Program
奈米國安局劃
Because I just remember people talking about Wikipedia
因為之前我只記得有人談維基電談什麼
he didn't talk about nano
他沒有談到奈米
So I also talked to that legislator
所以我也是跟那位立法委員
that legislator is famous
那立法委員有名
I won't say who this is now
我就現在這個不說是誰了
Then like him it was in the late 1990s
那麼跟他一樣都是在1990年代後期
I just had a meeting and found out that there is this thing
才稍稍開會知道有這個東西
Director Zhou graduated from the Department of Physics, National Taiwan University
周所長是台大物理系畢業的
In fact, I know that Director Zhou is already very famous in National Taiwan University.
事實上我知道周所長在台大已經是非常有名
we have fantastic students
我們有非常出色的學生
He then went to the University of California
之後他到美國加州大學
Ph.D. in Physics from Berkeley
博克萊分校拿到物理學博士
Then in Exxon
然後在Exxon公司
do this postdoc
做這個博士後
Since 1989 in
從1989年開始就在
Georgia Tech Institute of Technology
喬治亞理工大學理工學院擔任
Professor of Physics
物理系教授
In 1998, he became a professor of politics
1998年成為政教授
Then from 2005 to 2010
然後在2005到2010年
former department head
之前擔任系主任
He was taken by us in January this year
他在今年1月被我們
Come back to take charge of the camp
營品回來擔任
Director and Special Forces Researcher
所長兼特兵研究員
Especially the head of the State Council
尤其是國務院所長
The director's main research field is
所長主要研究領域是
Solid-state physics theory and first-principles calculations
固態物理理論跟第一原理計算
Especially in the application of materials
尤其所種在材料方面的應用
director of incoming research
所長進來的研究
including various heels
包括各種異圍跟
nanosystem
二圍的奈米系統
and solid scavenging materials
以及固體除清材料
He was in the internationally renowned
他曾在國際知名的
Rehabilitation has published more than 100 academic papers
康復發表過100多篇學術論文
Also had
此外也曾經得到過
country of america
美國的國家
Science Foundation's President's Young Scholar Award
科學基金會的總統年輕學者獎
and other important awards
以及其他的重要獎項
He is now a fellow of the American Physical Society
他現在是美國物理學會會事
And served as the chairman of the American Physical Society for the distribution of computational physics
而且曾經擔任美國物理學會計算物理分布的主席
As I just mentioned, since the 1990s
曾如我剛講到了二世紀90年代以來
Nano has become an important emerging field
奈米已經成為一個重要的新興領域
Many people, like me, thought that Nani and Penglaimi were the same thing in the 90s
很多人都像我一樣在90年代以為奈米跟蓬萊米是同一件東西
Now I think no one knows no one knows
現在我想無人不知無人不曉
And become part of the textbooks of elementary school, middle school and high school
而且成為小學中學高中以上課本的一部分
This was unimaginable in our time
這個在我們那個年代是沒有想到過的
he is an elective
他是一門選學
In the past 20 years in the development of nanoscience
過去20年在奈米科學發展中
Carbon meter has a very important position
碳計有非常重要的地位
The discovery and attention of carbon nanotubes, graphite, etc.
奈米碳管 石墨西等等的發現跟重視
is a very noteworthy thing
都是一個非常值得注意的事情
Last year's Nobel Prize in Physics was awarded to two scholars who made major breakthroughs in the study of graphite
去年諾貝爾物理獎就是頒給研究石墨西有重大突破的兩位學者
two russian scholars
兩位俄國學者
One of them came to the Central Plains to participate in the seminar shortly after winning the award
其中有一位就在得獎之後不久來到中原參加討論會
a very young man
一個非常年輕的年輕人
Master is an expert in nanomaterials
主掌是奈米材料的專家
Today his topic is
今天他題目是
carbon dimension official position
碳維也官職
Recent Developments in Nanomaterials
奈米材料的最新發展
I think this is a very interesting topic
我想這是一個非常有趣的題目
The number of participants today is unprecedented
今天參加人員盛況空前
Everyone, after listening today
各位今天聽完以後
It's just that nanometers are different from baked milk rice
就是到奈米跟烘奶米不同
We welcome the head of the seat
我們歡迎這個座首長
the baking problem
那個烘奶的問題
Thank you Vice President Wang
謝謝王副院長
Thank you all for coming to this evening's discussion
謝謝各位來參加今天晚上的討論
It's an honor to be with you all
感到很榮幸能跟大家
A little bit about the latest developments
稍微介紹一下最新的發展
That's what Vice President Wang said
那成如王副院長所說的
Nano this field
奈米這個領域
It's been about the past ten or fifteen years
已經大概在過去十年十五年
there's been a lot of progress
有非常非常多的進展
So what I want to introduce to you today
那今天我想跟大家介紹一下的呢
About the latest developments in nanomaterials
關於奈米材料最新的發展
Parts related to carbon
跟碳原素有關的部分
I think in this speaker I have noticed that
我想在這個議長我有注意到說
we have some younger friends
我們有一些比較年輕的朋友
There are also some who are doing some more senior
也有一些在做一些比較資深的
friend here
朋友在這裡
So I think our speaker should not be too polite
所以我想我們的議長不要太居行
Yes, if you think there is something wrong
是如果說大家覺得什麼地方有問題
raise your hand anytime
隨時都可以舉手
Not much package
不太有包打單
Because in some places, if you don't make it clear
因為有的地方如果沒有講清楚的話
Can it affect the following
可不可以影響到下面
I don't mind saying that people want to be able to
我不介意說大家希望能夠
straighten things out
馬上把一些事情弄清楚
so feel free to ask questions
所以隨時可以提出問題來
I think before we get to the subject
我想在我們講到這個主題之前
Because the topic is nanoscience with carbon
因為主題是個跟碳有關的奈米科學
I want to start with a quick introduction
我想先做一個很快的介紹
I think many of you have heard what nanoscience is
我想很多人都聽過什麼是奈米科學
So let's say I have a quick definition on my side
所以說我這邊有一個很快的定義
That is, we hope to be able to discuss
就是說我們再希望能夠探討
Or control because it is manipulate
或者調控因為是manipulate
at 1 to 100 nm
在1到100奈米
properties in matter of this size or so
這大小左右的物質中的特性
What about nanometers in our
那奈米呢在我們的這個
In the more professional language
比較專業的這個語言裡頭
Nano is actually turned upside down
奈米其實是翻過來的
English is called Nano
英文叫做Nano
so become nano
所以變成奈米
It is the power of time
它是時的腹久次方
So if we talk about a nano
所以說我們如果說一個奈米的話
It is the rice to the power of time multiplied by time
就是時乘上時的腹久次方的米
Nano means 100 centimeters
奈米的意思就是100公分
this size
這個大小
at this length
那在這樣子的長度下
It's a way you can imagine
是一種可以大家可以想像說
it's a very very very small unit
它是一個非常非常非常小的單位
Then in such a small place
那在這個到那麼小的地方的話
Maybe we can see atoms
大概我們就可以看到原子了
What about this length?
那在這樣子的這種長度之下呢
properties of objects
物體的特性
Many, many properties in the electronic properties
很多很多特性在電子的特性
or mechanical properties
或者機械方面特性
or optical properties
或者光學的性質
chemical properties
化學的性質
have basically changed
都有基本上的改變
that so
那所以
So in this case
所以說在這個情形下
We can make some special definitions
我們可以再做一些特別的定義
or special study
或者特別的學習
OK let it go
OK放過來
sorry
對不起
OK, so let me give you an analogy first
OK 所以像我先跟大家打個比方
I just felt what nanometer is called
剛剛感覺一下什麼叫做奈米
We can imagine that the earth is so big
我們可以想像說這個地球這麼大
OK then you have a small copper plate in your hand
OK 然後你手上拿一個小小的銅板
OK, what about the two ratios?
OK 那這個兩個比例呢
Like if say we shrink this down to
就像如果說我們把這縮到
A word of 1 meter and 100 centimeters
一個1米100公分的話
Then this copper plate is called a nanometer
那這個銅板就說到叫一個奈米
So we all know how big a copper plate is
所以我們大家都知道一個銅板有多大
We probably all know how big the earth is
我們大概也都知道地球有多大
It's their size difference
就是他們的那個大小的差別
So you would imagine saying
所以說你會想像說
where scientists can say
在科學家能夠說
from such a large unit
從這樣大的一個大的單位
into such a small world
進到這樣子一個小的世界
Then you can see something in it
然後在裡頭可以看到一些東西
to measure something
可以去測量一些東西
Yes, I can say that it is not an easy thing
是 我可以說是相當不簡單的事情
You can imagine that on earth
你可以想像說地球上
Let's say we're an alien
比如說我們一個外星人
an alien
一個外星人
Come to Earth in a spaceship outside
來到地球上在外面太空船
He wants to say you have a coin in your hand
他想要說你手上拿一個銅板
He wants to see what kind of words are written on the copper plate above you
他想要看到你上面銅板上什麼樣的字
You imagine it's a very, very difficult thing to do
你想像這是一個非常非常難的事情
He must have some special tools
他必須有一些特別的一些工具
come down and see
過下來看到
actually see what's on that copper plate
真正看到那個銅板上是什麼
What are we going to do now?
我們現在要做的事情呢
in a lab the size of ours now
就是在我們現在這樣子大小的實驗室裡頭
Able to enter a world of refugees
能夠進到一個難民的世界
Then see how it arranges atoms one by one
然後看到它一個個原子怎麼排
Then it has some form
然後它有一些什麼樣的形式
now this
現在這個
So this is our size above
所以這是我們的大小上面
So how will our situation change?
那我們什麼樣的情況會改變呢
This is a simple graph
這是一個簡單的圖
because mainly
因為主要在講
Quantum Confinement
Quantum Confinement
It's a quantum-bound problem
這是一個量子局限的問題
That is to say, if you assume a thing
就是說你假如一個東西
Once restricted by the bureau
一被局限制到的話
limited words
局限到的話
its nature will change
它的性質會改變
You probably imagine a situation like this
你大概想像說是一個這樣的情形
For example, if in classical history
譬如說假如說在古典歷學上
Let's look at a particle
我們看一個 particle
is a particle
就是一個粒子
It bumped and bumped and this side is sealed
它撞來撞去這邊被封住了
We can see it running around like this in there
我們可以看到它就在裡頭這樣跑來跑去
We can see a particle of this one object over there
我們可以看到它的這個一個物體的一個粒子在那邊
But in physics we have what's called quantum particle physics
可是在物理上我們有所謂的量子粒學
It doesn't matter if you haven't heard the term
如果大家還沒有聽過這個名詞的話沒有關係
I just want to mention the general things
我只要把大概的東西提一下
That is to say, in quantum particle physics
就是說在量子粒學裡面
a particle is not a particle
一個粒子並不是一個粒子
It's actually a fluctuating cold tree
它其實是一個波動的一個寒樹
And then when it fluctuates or is blocked in the middle
然後在它波動還是中間被封住的時候
it will have different of these waveforms
它就會有不同的這些波形
Then each waveform represents that it has different energy
那每個波形就代表它有不同的能量
So this is a very, very superficial way of speaking.
所以這個是非常非常很粗淺的一個講法
Then I think everyone probably has an experience
那我想大家大概都有一個經驗
For example, you've probably all seen a violin, a cello, or a guitar.
譬如說你們大概都看過小提琴、大提琴或是吉他
when you want to change the sound
那你要變不同的音的時候
You just change the length of the vibration of the string
你就把那個弦的震動的那個長度改變
right, according to different places
對不對,按不同的地方
When the length is changed, its frequency changes
那個長度改變以後它的頻率就變化了
Above Quantum Law
在量子率學以上
its that frequency
它的那個頻率
The frequency of that wave content
那個波含數的頻率
is its energy
就是它的能量
So if we put a direction
所以如果我們把一個方向
so restrict later
這樣限制住以後
it has changed a lot
它再發生了很多很多的變化
that when we are in this
那在我們在這種
What about the middle of this quantum confinement?
這種量子局限的中間呢
can have different limitations
可以有不同的局限
For example, we usually
譬如說我們通常
We are a three-dimensional space
我們是一個三維的空間
then we are in a certain area
那我們在某一個圍區
One direction confines it
一個方向把它限制住了
We become a two-dimensional system
我們變成一個二維的一個系統
We call this two-dimensional nanomode
我們這樣叫做二維的奈米模
it is one piece
它是一片的
Nano means its thickness
奈米的意思是說它的厚度
It's about a few nanometers
就是在大概幾個奈米左右
Then if we say
那我們如果說
If it is restricted in another direction
再一個方向又把它限制住的話
we'll see these
我們就會看到這些
This is one-dimensional into nanowires
這是一維的變成奈米線
This has both directions restricted
這有兩個方向都被限制住了
If we are restricted in three directions
如果我們三個方向都被限制住的話
i become a thing
我變成一顆東西
We are 0D
我們就是0維
GLD
GLD
0-dimensional nanoparticles
0維的奈米粒
In this case it's in our nanoscience
這樣情形下這是在我們那個奈米科學裡頭
see different systems
看到不同的系統
Then steal them they will belong to one of these
那偷辦他們會屬於這其中之一
from zero to one to two
從零為一到二為
What about the element carbon?
那在在碳這個元素來講呢
What I'll mention later is that
我等會提到的就是說
It actually has all three
它其實有三種都有
We'll see zeros like this
我們會看到有這樣子的零為的
this is a nanosphere
這是一個奈米球
Carbon is made up of carbon
碳這都是碳元素組成的
This is a nanometer carbon tube
這是一為的奈米的碳管
Each is a carbon atom or a binary
每個都是碳原子或者二為的
This is the graphite west we want to mention today
這是我們今天想要提的這個石墨西
The so-called Graphene
所謂的Graphene
It is a dual system
它是一個二為的系統
That's so wait a minute we'll all be back to this
這是所以等一下我們都會回到這樣子的
in each case i will mention
每個情形我都會提到
where are we in nanoscience
我們在奈米科學裡面呢
I want to clarify it again
我想再把它釐清一下
because it is a basically an emerging
因為它是一個基本上是一個新興的
interdisciplinary science
跨領域的科學
Because whether in chemical physics or biomaterials science
因為不管是在化學物理或生物材料科學
There are many engineering disciplines
還有許多的工程學科裡面
We are all slowly getting in touch with this aspect.
我們都會慢慢的都在跟這方面有些接觸
will also use some of the properties of nano
也都會運用奈米的一些性質
come and go on some of us
來去在我們一些
That is to say, to learn and explore some of its features
就是說去學習探討裡頭的一些特性
It has some emerging material properties
它有一些新興的材料性質
I probably want to wait for this
這個大概我想等會兒
maybe mention an example or two
可能會提一兩個例子
we study nanoscience
我們研究奈米科學中
We also need to develop new measurement and control tools
我們還要發展新的量測和控制的工具
into what I just said
成我剛剛所講的話
we're going to a very small place
我們要到一個很小很小的地方去
If you can measure something very accurately
能夠很精確的測量一些東西的話
There are many tools that must be developed
有很多工具必須要發展出來
Then Nano can now also be applied to some
然後奈米現在也可以應用到一些
health care energy or electronics
健康保健能源或電子上
Some technology and design above electronic science
電子科學上面的一些技術和設計
these are in progress
這些都在進行當中
Then usually we are in this nano
那通常我們在這個奈米的這個
inside the field
領域裡頭
very important also
很重要的一點也很
it takes a lot of time
相當花很多時間的話
is to understand the interaction between matter
是去了解物質間的相互左右
especially in such a small
尤其是在那麼小的一個
in that length
那種長度裡面
What about this whole science?
那這個這整個科學呢
still in development
現在還是一直在發展之中
We have several practical application strengths
我們有幾項實際上的應用實力
wait might mention it
等一下可能會提到一下
most research and development projects
大多數的研究發展項目
still in progress
還在進行當中
I think what you can expect is to say
我想各位可以期望的就是說
The future is in five or ten years
未來在五年十年之中
You will continue to hear that
各位還是會不斷的聽到說
There are many new applications of nano
有很多新的奈米方面的應用
or nano
或者奈米方面的
that emerging technology
那個新興的技術
in development
在發展當中
So this is a very simple generalization
所以這是一個很簡單的一個概論
How will nanotechnology affect our lives?
那奈米科技將如何影響我們的生活呢
I'm just starting out here and I want to use a couple of examples
我這邊剛開始我想用幾個例子
This is not directly related to the carbon we are talking about today.
這個跟我們今天講到的碳的並不是直接相關
But I think there are a few more interesting situations
可是我想也有幾個比較有趣的情形
The first one is to say that this is already being done
第一個就是說這個已經在都已經在做了
We all know that pitch first
我們大家都知道說那個pitch first
Everyone knows that you take a peach
大家知道那個你拿一個桃子
That surface is furry, isn't it?
那表面是毛茸茸的對不對
So for this thing, you drop a water on it
所以這個東西的話你滴一個水上去
it won't stick
它不會沾上去
The water turned into pieces and slipped away.
那個些水都變成一顆一顆就滑掉了
Then we usually wear clothes
那我們平常穿衣服
you go to something
你就到去到參加什麼東西
have a drink
喝一杯飲料
What you are most afraid of is that the drink is spilled on you
你最怕的就是說飲料灑到你的身上去了
then get naked
然後弄得一身不開
if there was a way to say something to you
假如有個辦法說你東西
As soon as these liquids are sprinkled on
這些 liquid 這些液體東西一灑上去
become like this ball
都變成這樣子球狀
and then go away like this
然後就會這樣子滾開
won't get it wet
不會把它沾濕
that's not a very good thing
那這不是非常好的事情
If you sprinkle it, you will pat it
你這灑上去你就拍拍
it just shoots and it goes away
它就拍下來它就走了
I wouldn't say that I stained that dress.
就不會說把那個衣服弄髒了
So now there are some techniques that say
所以現在有一些技術就是說
We can use 10 nanometer
我們可以用10個奈米的
The carbon one that is so long
這麼長的那個carbon的那個
that little kind of fiber
那種小小的那種纖維
What about this kind of thing?
那這種東西呢
It will be the same as the cotton fiber in our place
會跟我們這裡頭的棉花纖維是會
that is to say it fits together
就是說很結合在一起
In this way, on this surface
這樣子的話在這個表面上
formed
就形成了一下
Like our pick a peach on the surface
像我們那個拿個桃子表面上
that furry
那個毛茸茸的
Except you can't see that furry now
只不過你現在看不到那個毛茸茸的
because that thing is so small
因為那東西實在太小了
In such a situation
那這樣子的情形下的話
it will generate say on this surface
它會把產生說在這個表面
those with some very small air
有一些很小的空氣的那些存在
with those on these fibers
跟那些這些纖維上面
there will be one separated
會有一個隔起來
So when those liquids fell on top
所以當那些液體跌到上面的時候
It turns into a ball like this
它就這樣子變成圓珠
and you'll be gone
然後你就會滾開了
things already done
已經在做到的事情
called fancy pants
叫 fancy pants
This is called stain resistance
這叫 stain resistance
just won't stain
就是不會沾污掉
that's something that's been done now
那這是一個現在已經做到的東西
Of course, what is the real principle behind the application here?
那當然這裡頭應用的真正裡頭的原理呢
It’s just a lot of things that Lu Yuan can’t see now.
就是很多像我們看現在路遠看不到的東西
very small inside
裡頭很小很小的
carbon fiber
碳的那個纖維
fibers that can be compared with cotton
可以跟棉花的纖維
can be held together tightly
可以緊緊的結合在一起
Of course, this is what we want if we say
當然這個東西也是我們要如果說
Do many, many dives with a very powerful baggage machine
用很強的行李機去潛多很多很多次
Then the surface will inevitably come off
那不免表面就會脫了一下
slowly it will get wet
慢慢慢慢它會濕掉一些
wet some of these features
濕掉一些這些功能
The basic principle of this design is
那這個設計就是基本上的原理就是
is to imitate
也是就是要模仿
the surface of our peach
我們那個桃子表面
Let's see if those fluffy ones can do it
那些毛絨絨的看能不能做到
man-made structures
人造的這些一些結構
What about another example?
那另外一個例子呢
This is probably now probably a
這個可能現在大概是一個
Compare a Vision of Yuancheng
比較院城的一個願景
hope it can be done
希望能做到是
That is to say, we take the very small particles of Nimi
就是说我们拿很小很小的那些耐米的粒子
What we call Nano-crystal is a very small crystal
我们所谓的Nano-crystal就是很小的晶体
The four particles of ordinary people are Cadence Selenite, which is a composite
那一般人这四个粒子是Cadence Selenite是一种合成物
it's very very it has some special properties
那它非常非常的它有一些特别的性质
That is to say, when it reaches very small particles
就是说当它到很小的粒子的时候
like we can follow its size
像我们可以依照它的大小
Then it has different levels of different energies
然后它有不同的能量的能级的不同的levels
So in this is a photo just say
所以说在这是一个照片就说
If we shine a light on it and it shines some ultraviolet light
如果我们照一个它照射一些紫外光
after absorbing the light
吸收了那光以后
it has different energy levels
它有不同的能阶
so it shines
所以它会放光
The colors of these radiances are based on the difference in energy levels
那这些放光的颜色就根据它能阶的差别
The years are determined by size
这些年间是由大小来决定的
So in this is an experiment just say
所以在这是一个实验就说
If placed in some agriculture
如果放在一些農業裡面
Then shine these dead lights
然後照這些死外光
Then you will find that it has different colors
然後你會發現它有不同的顏色
so according to the color
所以照這的顏色
You know what size it is
你就知道說它這個大小是多少
That kind of example is very small
那這種例子是很小
Now someone is thinking about saying
那現在有人在考慮說
Because this thing can hear the human body
因為這個東西可以聽到人體
can penetrate many things in your studies
就可以穿透很多東西在你學業中
So and it superficially can
所以而且它表面可以
we can put some antibodies on it
我們可以把它放一些抗體
put something that is not external
放一些不外在的東西
Then it can carry the body of this station
那它可以帶著這個站的人體裡頭
walk through school
在學業裡頭走過去
that this is an experiment
那這個是一個實驗
Let's say it puts some
假如說它在外面放了一些
These antibodies antibody
這些抗體antibody
It interacts with proteins emitted by certain IC packets
它會跟某些IC包放出的蛋白質
They serve the function
它們會服藏作用
So after it enters the human body
所以它進到人體以後
it goes where it likes
它就去找它喜歡的地方
with those proteins
跟那些蛋白質放在一起
When we take these little nanometers for example
當我們當這些小的奈米這些例子
to the female part of the animal
到了這個動物體裡頭的母部分
In the vicinity of inflammatory needle cancer cells
在炎針癌細胞的附近的話
it just stays there
它就停留在那裡
If so
那這樣子的話
If we shine another UV light outside
如果我們外面再照一下紫外光
Then the light is absorbed by it
那這些光就被它吸收到
Then you start to shine over there
然後你就那邊開始放光
so this is an experiment
所以這是一個實驗
experiment with mice
用老鼠來做實驗
Then it will also be able to detect
然後也會能夠偵測到
where the cancer cells are
這個癌細胞所在的地方
So this is of course what to do in the future
所以這是當然是做將來的話
Hope to use this technique
希望能夠用這個技術
It can be said that there are these detections of this cancer
能夠說有這個癌症的這些偵測
Tell me where the cancer cells started to grow
說東西什麼地方開始長癌細胞了
So of course it's a very long term one
所以當然這是非常長遠的一個
hope to achieve something
希望能夠達到的東西
Also this is
另外還有這是
This is relatively new
這個是比較新的東西
a result of last year
去年的一個結果
That is what we call artificial skin
就是說我們所謂的 artificial skin
artificial skin
就是人造皮膚
we shine in our skin
我們照我們的皮膚
has a very important special function
有一個很重要的特別的功能
that is
就是說
You can feel it when you touch it
摸上去你就有感觉
right
对不对
Because we feel pressure after we touch it
因为我们摸上去以后有压力
So if say
所以说如果说
We're going to take an artificial skin
我们要照一个人造皮肤
you have to touch to put pressure
你要摸上去要把压力
what about stress
然后压力呢
to convey
要传达出来
words expressed by some signals
用一些信号表示出来的话
you have to amplify those signals
你必须把那些信号放大
and then with some current
然后用一些电流的方式
convey it
把它传达出来
So when people study and say
所以当大家研究说
What to do when taking photos of these artificial skins
怎么样去照这些人造皮肤的时候
It actually uses some
它其实它用了一些
Zoomed out here are some rice noodles
在这放大出来的这是一些耐米线
Here
在这边
Because of rice noodle it has some functions
因为耐米线它有一些功能
That is, it can be used as an electrolytic body
就是它可以作为一个电经体
it amplifies a signal
它会把一个信号放大
So in a layer
所以在某一层里头
It bought a lot of rice noodles
它就买了很多耐米线
Then these artificial skins
然后这些人造的皮肤
it is very it can bend
它是非常它可以弯曲
Then it can have a layer on top of that
然后它可以上面有一层就是
something that detects stress
可以侦测压力的东西
and pass that signal down
然后把那个信号传递下去
Then use this rice noodle
然后用这个耐米线
Send out the signal of this current
把这个电流的信号送出来
so we know
所以我们知道
So measure the pressure everywhere
所以测到每个地方有压力
so this is a
所以这是一个
can now
现在能够
a situation that does
做到的一個情形
Then it needs that very low voltage to operate
然後它需要很低的那個電壓就可以運作
Sometimes you need other systems
有時候你需要有的其他系統
May require a lot of voltage
可能需要很大的電壓
so not ideal
所以不是很理想
So how many
所以說有幾個
There are several applications of this
這方面有幾個應用
after our course
在我們當然以後
I want to spend the next five to ten years
我想在過未來的五年到十年
You will still hear a lot of new things coming out
大家還是會聽到很多新的東西出來
OK
OK
All right
All right
ok now let's get back to the topic
好 現在我們先回到主題
Let's talk about the role that look plays in this nanoscience
我們講看在這個奈米科學中扮演的角色
OK
OK
if you still
如果大家還
Probably everyone should have heard of the periodic table of the elements.
大概都應該都聽過這元素的周期表
right
對
Look at the elements
看元素呢
Here
在這邊
it is there
它是有
Its atomic sequence is six
它的原子序列是六
There are twelve electrons
有十二個電子
right
對
it's not a metal
它不是一個金屬
It's right on top of the Sircum department
它正好在Sircum這個系的上面
that they have the same
就是它們有同樣的
very similar electronic structure
很相似的電子結構
There are many, many on our planet
那在我們地球上是很多很多的
inside our body
我們身體裡面
big pile
一大堆胎
eat every day
每天吃東西
fetal water compound
胎水化合物
then physically
然後身體上
all those molecules
所有的那些分子
A lot of them contain fetal atoms
一大堆都含有胎原子在裡面
Then our entire organic chemistry
然後我們這整個的有機化學裡頭
It's the fluid element
就是流動胎者元素
That 20% of the human body is actually fetal atoms
那20%的人體其實是胎原子
but the fetal atom it is a
但是胎原子它是一個
kaleidoscopic elements
千變萬化的元素
because it has many
因為它有很多很多
it can do many, many things
它可以做很多很多事情
We take the fetal atom out like this
我們把胎原子這樣把它拿出來
put it together
把它放在一起
It wants it to form very different images
它要它會形成極有不同的像
Everyone knows the first diamond
第一個大家都知道鑽石
diamond is tire
鑽石是胎
In fact, fetal element is in it
其實是胎原素在裡面
or stone wood
或者石木
It's still the black one in the pencil
還是鉛筆裡面那個黑黑的
That's a tire
那也是胎
placenta
都是胎原素
Those two are completely different situations
那這兩個都是完全不一樣的情形
that's inside the nami structure
那在耐米結構裡面
placenta will be formed
胎原素會有形成
I can even mention Naimi's carbon
我都可以提一下耐米的碳
it is spherical
它是有球狀的
or carbon nanotubes
或是奈米的碳管
And now the latest material
還有現在最新的材料
graphite west it is a flat
石墨西它是一個平面的
There are already two
那在這裡面已經有兩個
Liu Boer talked about a chemistry
劉伯爾講了一個是化學
carbon nanospheres
是在奈米碳球
then one is physical
然後一個是物理
Said it was last year's graphite west
講是去年的石墨西
I'll put this over here later
那這個等會我會把這邊
Let me talk about it a little bit
稍微提出來講一下
so our
那所以我們的
now everyone's
現在大家的
just like that
就這樣子就是說
What about carbon?
碳元素呢
In fact, in our
其實是在我們這個
that nano
那個奈米
Inside the Science of Nanotechnology
科學的奈米技術裡頭
actually very very important
其實是非常非常重要的
Member of Parliament
議員
then let's go back first
那我們先回去
look at this
看一下這個
diamond and graphite
鑽石跟石墨
let's get to know
我們先瞭解一下
it is at
它在
our kind
我們這種
before going to nano
在進到奈米之前
what kind of properties will it have
它會有一些什麼樣的性質
If you have taken chemistry in high school
如果大家修過高中的化學
I don't think anyone is unfamiliar with this
我想對這個都不會陌生
because in carbon
因為在碳元素裡面
we usually talk about that
我們通常講到那個
when the electronic structure
電子結構的時候
We have two different energy levels
我們是有兩個不同的能階
Then this is our tree feather
那這個我們的樹羽
Then there are 2S and 2P
然後就是2S跟2P
An A4 and P
一個A4跟P
two different tracks
兩個不同的軌道
that in its ground state
那在它的基態
The ground state is the lowest energy situation
ground state就是最低能量的情形
We have to consider four electrons outside
我們要考慮四個電子在外面
So these two are in the track of A4
所以這兩個在A4這個軌道裡面
The remaining two are in the P orbital
另外剩下兩個在P軌道裡面
So this is the lowest energy
那這樣這是最低能量
But since the two are quite close
可是因為這兩個相當接近
so sometimes
所以有的時候
it goes to a higher level
它會進到一個比較高階
a comparatively excited state
一種比較激發態
Then move the electron up again
那再次把這個電子移上去
One on A4 and three on P
一個在A4 三個在P
So in this case
所以在這個情形下
the two of them will
他們這兩個會
probably mixed up
大概會混在一起
we are called
我們叫做
In chemistry it is called hybridization
在化學上叫做hybridization
put the two together
就把兩個合在一起了
that becomes four together
那變成四個在一起
called SP3
叫做SP3
if four together
如果四個在一起的話
If we paint this out
我們如果把這個塗化出來
A4 is usually a spherical
A4通常是一個球狀的
It is directional, up, down, left, right, front, back
是有方向性的上下左右前後
So when added together like this
所以這樣加在一起的時候
The hybrid orbiton of sp3 has a directionality
sp3這個hybrid orbiton就有一個方向性
Then this directionality means
那這個方向性就是說
There are four outside the middle one
中間一個外面有四個
So if this is the case
所以這樣子的話
In the formation of the structure of most so-called diamonds
在形成的最所謂的鑽石的結構
That is to say, any climbing atom
就是說任何一個攀原子
There are four climbing atoms nearby
附近都有四個攀原子在那裡
Then this structure is a very, very stable
那這個結構是一個非常非常穩定
then very very
然後非常非常
That is to say, it will not be accepted by outsiders
就是說不會被外接受
a structure of interference
干擾的一個結構
that's very very strong
那這非常非常強的
That kind of chemistry is made up here
那種化學件在這邊組成
the structure like this
那這樣子的結構
That is, it is in our visible light
就是它是在我們可見光裡頭
It does not absorb visible light
它是不會吸收可見光的
So let's say we see transparent diamonds
所以說我們看到透明的鑽石
and then the whole thing is very, very hard
然後整個東西非常非常硬
because it's hard to compress it
因為它很難把它壓縮
so it's just
所以它只是
Because of its arrangement
由於它這個排列方式
and because of it this
然後由於它這個
the number of electrons it has
它有的電子數目
and decided to say that a physical property of it like this
而決定說它這樣子的一個物理性質
of course this
那當然這個
This is the distance between its atomic rulers
這是它的原子原尺中間的距離
Of course it's small
當然是很小的
Also on the Nano side
也是在奈米方面
Calculated in temperature nanometers
以溫奈米來計算
so this is in
那所以這是在
Because of this arrangement
因為這樣子的排列
Put Taiyuan Quality Sauce Together
把太原質醬放在一起
it turns into a diamond
它變成鑽石
If we say we are too primitive
那如果說我們太原質
another arrangement
另外一種排列
becomes
就變成
turned into stone membrane
變成石膜了
become the stuff in our pencils
變成我們鉛筆中的材料了
Also Taiyuan
同樣也是太原質
But what?
可是呢
We when we got to this house to stimulate the tires
我們當我們到這家激發胎的時候
i don't take it all
我不是拿把所有的
Three plus three and four all put together
三個加三個四個都放在一起
I take the top and take two
我是拿上面拿兩個
Take one here and turn it into SP2
這邊拿一個變成SP2
Then leave the other one there
然後剩下一個就丟在那邊
no matter where it is placed
不管它放在那邊
It does not interact with others by itself
它自己不跟其他的去作用
If you make it like this
那這樣子弄起來的話
SP2 is an S is an original
SP2的話是一個S是一個原的
What about the other two P's?
那另外那個兩個P的話
One is horizontal and the other is heavy
一個就在橫一個在重的方面
So to combine it becomes one
所以要結合起來就變成一個
called sp2 becomes an angle of 120 degrees
叫做sp2变成120度的一个角度
so it you turn things 120 degrees
所以它你要把东西变成120度
Then line up the words
然后排列出来的话
It's a Ginger like this
就是一个这样子的金格
It has three per atom
每一个摊原子它都有三个
it's in the booth atom it to the neighborhood
它的在摊原子它到附近
Then they form an angle of 120 degrees
然后它们形的角度是120度
a plane like this
这样子的一个平面
line it up
把它排列起来
Because we live in a three-dimensional space
因为我们生活在一个三维的空间
So all matter is three-dimensional
所以所有的物质都是三维的
If they are lined up, they will become the graphite kilometer stars we are talking about.
排起来的话就变成我们讲的石墨千米星
In fact, there are stalls inside
其实里面也都是摊
everything is the same
每个东西都一样
So the complete foundation is built according to its arrangement
所以说完全基造根据它的排列
Its electronic structure will be different
它的电子结构会不一样
And on this plane
而且在这个平面上
Its layer-by-layer effects are very weak
它的一层一层的那些作用是很弱的
Most of the strong action is on this plane
多半的强作用都在这个平面上
So it's a very soft thing
所以说它是一个很软的东西
We can use it as kilometers
我们能够把它用作千米
you write on paper
你写在纸上
why does it get out on paper
为什么它会在纸上弄出
Because the relationship between them is too light
因為說他們之間的作用實在是太輕了
So the layers will peel off
所以說一層一層之間會剝裂
That's why it has properties like this
所以它才會有這樣子的性質
This is what we see in these
這是它在我們看到的這些
matter that existed
原來就存在的物質
something in nature
大自然中就有的東西
That's the nano world
那到了奈米世界
we have to make it
我們要必須要去製造它
Rearrange these electrons from scratch
把這些電子從頭再排列一下
The only possibility is
唯一的可能性也就是
The whole nature has only two kinds
整個的那個性質也就只有兩種
SP2 is arranged in a plane like this
SP2以這樣子的一個平面的一個排列
Or like that diamond we just saw
或者是我們剛剛看到的那個鑽石那樣子
This is an arrangement of measurements
這是一個三圍的一個排列
In fact, only these two
其實就只有這兩種
So let's say that in this
所以說在我們想在這個
throughout the development
整個發展路程中
Now this is 1996
現在這個是1996年
in the lab
在實驗室裡面
there are three scientists
有三個科學家
They made a new one
他們把製造出了一個新的一個
The quest for materials called nanometers
材料所謂的奈米的探求
basically
基本上呢
take sixty atoms
拿六十個原子
put it together
把它湊在一起
Then form a structure
然後形成的一個結構
like a ball like this
就像一個這樣子的一個球狀
The so-called Buddy ball
所謂的Buddy ball
what about this thing
這個東西呢
the football we all know
跟我們大家所知的那個足球
Take a football and have a look
你拿一個足球來看一看
it's the exact same thing
這是一模一樣的東西
We are at this time when everyone is doing football
我們在這個大家做足球的時候
have found that
已經發現說
This way you can make a spherical thing
這樣子可以做出一個圓球性的東西
let's look at this thing
我們看這個東西
you will find that say
你會發現說
how to see it here
這裡頭怎麼去看它
This side is a hexagon
這一面是六角形
That black place is a pentagon
那個黑的地方是五角形
Then each dot is a bomb atom
那每一個點都是一個彈原子
So for any bomb atom
所以對一個任何一個彈原子來講
it has three bomb atoms next to it
它都有三個彈原子在它旁邊
Live because
直播點是因為
flat time
平面的時候
each is three
每一個都是三個
So everyone is equal
所以大家全部都是平的
when you hear this
聽到這樣子的情形下
if i were to bend it down
如果說我要把它彎下的話
i must have a place
我一定有一個地方
less than six
都湊不到六個
so just
所以就
It's all pentagonal
都變成五角形了
so you can go back and get
所以你回去可以拿
If you are interested, you can take a picture yourself
有興趣的話自己可以拍拍看
this is a quest
這就是一個探求
then at this time
那在這個時候
When everyone is doing it in the lab
大家在實驗室裡頭做的時候
It's just a picture bar that puts a bunch of suns together
就是把一大堆太陽擺在一起的圖欄
formed between them
他們之間就形成了
found a special structure like this
找到了一個這樣子一個特別的結構
Then a structure like this is a new form
那這樣子一個結構是一個新的形式
Because everyone thinks that
因為這個大家以為說
we never saw this thing
我們從來沒有看過這個東西
Thought we made it in the lab
以為是我們在實驗室裡頭造出來的
This was in the 90s
這個在九零年代那個時候
By the time of 2000, two thousand years
到二零叫兩千年的時候
There are many, many applications
有很多很多的應用
You have done a lot of research
大家做了很多很多的研究
that last year
那最近在去年
only found out in astronomy school
在天文學校才發現說
Possibly far, far away in outer space
可能在很遠很遠外面的外太空
inside these nebulae
這些星雲裡面
Discovery of a nebula 6,000 light-years away
發現一個六千光年以外的一個星雲
Maybe something like this already existed at that time
可能那個時候已經有這樣子的東西存在
That's why I found out
所以才發現說
This stuff maybe not that we hear
這東西也許不是說我們聽到
first made
第一個做出來的
a structure like this
這樣子的一個結構
What kind of a property will there be
會有什麼樣的一個性質
why they won the nobel prize
為什麼他們會得了諾貝爾獎
to make something like this
來製造出這樣的東西
because yes it is very very
因為是它是非常非常
very very strong first time
第一次非常非常強
Because these chemical circles are not easily broken
因為這些化學界是不容易被打破的
So basically the ball is very stable
所以基本上球是很穩定的
very stable ball
很穩定的一個球
Ordinary people please imagine
一般人請想像說
This surface can attach some
這個表面可以附著一些
many other things
很多其他的東西
For example, the molecules of some drugs
譬如說把一些藥的那些分子
can put it on top
可以把它上面
Then everyone was imagining at that time that
然後大家在那個時候在想像說
I can put this thing in my studies
我可以把這個東西放到學業裡頭去
It can take things to where you tell it to deliver
它就可以把東西帶到你所要叫它送的地方
because this is small
因為這種很小
it doesn't work with anything else
它不跟別的東西在去作用
Then it might be able to cross those cell membranes
然後它也許可以穿越那些細胞膜
or some places
或者是一些地方
So for something like this is equal to a unit
所以對於這樣子的等於是一個單位
we can bring
我們可以拿來
Just say Manupay
就說Manuplay
use it to do
拿來去做
do something
做一些東西
That is about after this discovery
那就是大概在這個發現之後
late 90's
90年代後期
or 10 years ago
或者是10年以前
That stuff is pretty, really hot
那這個東西是相當相當熱門
everyone told him
大家都對他說
this is a new thing
這是一個新的東西
we all have to think about it
我們都要去想想看
what kind of that thing can we use
我們可以用什麼樣的那個東西
It can be found that it has some functions
可以發現它有些功能
or for special applications
或者是拿來做特別的應用
so this is the first
那所以這是第一個
Judgment-related refugee structure
和判有關的難民結構
what about later
那在後來呢
Next step
下一步
What we found was that
我們發現的是說
We can use the structure just like that
我們可以用剛剛那樣子的那樣結構
not make a ball
不是做一個球
i can make him a pipe
我可以把他做一個管子
roll it up
把它捲起來
make a pipe
做一個管子
When making pipes like this
那這樣子做管子的時候
depends on how you roll
就看你怎麼捲
have different directions
有不同的方向
So after that we have some terms
所以之後我們有一些術語
this is called
這叫做
pull towards CZAC like a chair
像一個椅子一樣的拉向CZAC
That is to say, in a different direction
就是說不同的這個方向
their nature will be different
他們的性質也會不一樣
some will be semiconductor
有的會是半導體
Some will be very conductive
有的會是導電性很好
So if say we take a
所以說如果說我們拿一個
A carbon nanotube
半導體的一個奈米碳管
And what about these
然後這些呢
It can go to the surface to absorb some
它可以去表面吸附一些
other molecules
其他的分子
Then we can go and measure these conductivities
然後我們可以去量測這些導電度
Then those molecules change the conductivity
那這些分子就改變導電度
So these carbon nanotubes
所以這些奈米碳管
can become a
就可以變成是一個
become a sensor
變成一個sensor
That is to say very sensitive
就是說很感應
some can go to measure some
一些可以去測量一些
A tool for other molecules
其他的分子的一個工具
and at the same time
然後同時呢
We also made some
我們也用它做過一些
Flight Panel Display
Flight Panel Display
The screen you made
你們做的那個這個螢幕
Everyone has to make it thinner and thinner
大家要做得越來越薄
Then use less power
然後要用電量越小
What about carbon tubes?
那這個其實碳管呢
It's actually a good material
其實是一個很好的材料
it can be released in some of the
它可以放出在某些那個
The release of electrons under voltage has many effects
電壓下放出電子有很多的效果
It is said that some electronic companies are already making such products
這有所謂有些電子公司已經在做這樣的產品
So this has only had two covers in the past
所以這個在以往只有兩個封面
This is our first science magazine
這是我們先科學雜誌上
Usually there are many, many articles about these stamina probes for a while
通常都在有一陣子很多很多文章關於這些耐力探管
So this was probably before this 2010
所以這大概是在這個 2010 年以前
to every scientific federation
到每一個科學的聯會上
Lots and lots of discussion about this material
就一大堆的很多的討論關於這個材料
These are the words that probably speak to us
這些都是大概對我們來講的話
It's already the first wave
都是已經是第一波了
In 2006 five or six years ago
在 2006 五六年前
Everyone started to find out
大家開始發現說
In addition, there is another thing
另外其實還有一個東西
This is what I've been looking for
就是我一直想要找的就是這一片
The so-called graphite west
所謂的這個石墨西
This piece of stuff is taken out of the graphite
這一片的東西從石墨裡頭拿出來
Then it will be a very good two-dimensional nanostructure
那它會是一個很好的一個二維的一個奈米結構
That's because it's only one atom thick
那這個因為這只有一個原子那麼厚而已
So if other probes that we see like this nano
所以如果其他我們看到的像這種奈米的探球
or probe
或者探管
In fact, it is to take this part to roll up
其實就是拿這一部分來把捲起來
or wrap it up like this
或者是把它繞捲起來這樣子
Or we take layer by layer what we call graphite
或者我們拿一層一層來就是我們所說的石墨
So this is something that people are looking for
所以這個東西是一個大家想要尋找
Probably hope to be able to separate it
大概希望能夠把它分離出來
Then I hope to be able to use it for another goal I want to achieve
然後希望能夠用它的另外一個想要達到的一個目標
Then we call a structure like this Graphene
那這個這樣子的一個結構我們叫做Graphene
As far as graphite is concerned, it has SP2 as we just mentioned
就石墨西它是有剛剛我們講過是SP2
So the angle of each of them is 120 degrees
所以它每一個的那個角度都是120度
Remind me like this again
再這樣子提醒一下
The Graphite West Phenomenon Since 2004
這個石墨西的現象從2004年開始
Everyone has the first article introduction
大家有第一篇的文章介紹
For example, say that I can do this
比如說表示說我可以做到這件事情
This is the paper that everyone will publish in the future
以後這是大家所發表的論文
Papers published worldwide
全世界發表的論文
So you can see that this increase is unwilling to rise
所以你看它這個增加是不願上升
So this trend is pretty pretty amazing
所以這個趨勢是相當相當驚人的
this paper daily paper
這個論文每天論文
You can imagine that there are many students
你都會想像說有很多學生
Or a researcher working in a lab for a few months
或者是研究人員在實驗室裡頭做好幾個月
Then take this result and write it out
然後採取把這個結果寫出來
I finally wrote a paper
好不容易寫出了一篇論文
In the past few years has been in this
在過去幾年中已經在這個
This is a Xinjiang with more than a few thousand
這是一個新疆多於幾千
Eight thousand papers have come out
八千篇論文已經出來了
But many, many people from different fields
但很多很多不同領域的人
all wanting to find in it says
都在想要在裡面都會發現說
there's something in here
這裡頭有些東西
We can research and use it on my topic
我們可以研究可以用到我的題目上
So throughout the development
所以在整個的發展中
in a column
在某一個專欄
He just said something like this
他就提了這樣子一句話
他說Graphic Mentor to be Lady Gaga of Materials
他說Graphic Mentor to be Lady Gaga of Materials
say that for the material
說這對材料而言
it's possible
這是可能是
It's a goddess, everyone knows why
就是女神大家知道為什麼
like this he said
就這樣子他說
seems to be from
好像是從
It seems to come from nowhere
It seems to come from nowhere
He came out of nowhere
他不曉得從哪裡冒出來的
Then
然後
everyone is talking about him
每個人都在談論他
Then what
然後呢
not long
沒有多久
He is going to be absolutely everywhere
He is going to be absolutely everywhere
you are not eating
你不在吃
see him everywhere
各個地方都看到他
so we all the world
所以我們大家全世界
I see this news everywhere
各個地方都看到這個消息
So for now
所以說在目前來講
This is a
這是一個
That is to say, many, many researchers
就是說很多很多研究人員都
found some special
在裡頭發現了一些特別的
special subject
性質受特別做的題目
the whole
這個整個的
the whole trend
整個的趨勢
The whole phenomenon started in 2004
整個現象是在2004年開始的
that's the first paper
那這是第一篇論文
these two
是這兩位呢
is now the first two
就是現在就是頭兩位
The first two were taken later
就是頭兩位就是後來拿了
These two Nobel Prize winners
諾白獎的這兩位
British scientists
英國的科學家
Then this place this article
那這個地方這篇文章
is talking
是講到說
This thing is actually a transistor thing
這個東西其實是一個電晶體的東西
他說atomic to the thing carbon films
他說atomic to the thing carbon films
everyone understands this
大家懂這個意思
which means it's very, very thin
就是說它非常非常薄
It is a two-dimensional thin film
它是一個二維的一個薄膜
He said he separated it
那他說把它分離出來了
Why can't I get it?
為什麼而會得到不來講呢
That's mainly because it mentions one thing here
那主要是它這裡提到了一個事情
That is to say, this article confirms that
就是說這篇文章確認了就是說
We can use it as a material for transistors
我們可以把它拿來作為電晶體的材料
Everyone knows that transistors are a very important
大家都知道電晶體是一個非常重要
on electronic circle
在電子圓件上
important things
重要的東西
I'll talk about it later
那我等一下會講一下
Why do you think this is
為什麼大家覺得這是
Will do transistor material
會做電晶體材料
will be so so so important
會這麼這麼這麼重要
Then it is here to say
那它是在這邊是說
they found out
他們發現了說
This can be used as a feel effect transistor
這可以作為一個feel effect transistor
Then it can be used with
然後它可以用
It can do some switch
它可以去做一些switch
that is, the one that changes it
就是說改變它的那個
The thing that replaces the charged particles inside
裡頭的那個代電粒子的東西
can have a great function
可以有很大的功能
and the reason it won the prize
然後它得獎的那個原因
because it
是因為它
Can be equal to a new field of innovation
能夠等於說創新的一個新的領域
they mean
他們是就是說
words displayed
顯示出來的話
This thing has big, big potential
這個東西有很大很大的潛力
Then they are the first to be able to
然後他們第一個能夠
able to make the first measurement
能夠把第一個測量給做出來
It's actually a very, very simple experiment.
其實這是一個非常非常簡單的實驗
Everyone thinks that physicists need very complicated and complicated instruments to do experiments.
大家以為說物理學家做實驗要有很複雜很複雜的儀器
or to do
或者是要做
In this experiment it is actually very simple
在這個實驗中其實是很簡單
That is to say, after this article comes out
就是說這文章一出來以後
In fact, many, many laboratories can
實際上很多很多的實驗室都可以
do this next
都接下來做這件事情
In fact, this lab in many schools
我其實這個很多學校裡頭的實驗室
also started to be able to make it out
也開始能夠去把它做出來
Because the procedure in this lab is actually very simple
因為這個實驗室的程序其實是非常簡單的
Of course now slowly everyone wants to take that
當然現在慢慢慢慢大家想要把那個
The system is getting cleaner
系統弄得越來越乾淨
there is a new way
那有新的方法
OK
OK
Then see the dashboard
那看到 dashboard
Before I get to the following
在我到下面這個之前
because how to do this experiment
因為去怎麼做這個實驗
This is a very interesting phenomenon
這是一個非常有趣的一個現象
I usually show this to my students, which means
我在通常都會給學生看這個就是說
It will tell you how to do it on YouTube
在YouTube裡頭就會告訴你說你怎麼去做
So what he did was simple
所以他做的事情很簡單
get one of your tapes
拿你的一個膠帶
then you take a
然後你拿一個
Pick out that pencil heart
把那個鉛筆心裡頭挑出來
on top of the tape
放在膠帶上面
You know the pencil has many, many, many layers in its heart
你知道鉛筆心裡頭就拾摸它很多很多很多層
Every floor is very close
每層每層很近
usually you take a small one
通常你拿一個小小的一個
There are about a few million layers in mm
mm的時候大概有幾百萬層
But it doesn't matter, he just uses tape like this
不過沒有關係他就用這樣膠帶呢
don't want to be like
就不想像是
inone to stick together and separate
inone把黏在一起再分開
He is like saying that I have split several layers
他等於說我分掉了好幾層
look like this
你看這樣子
really really really they do it
真的真的真的他們這樣做出來
can do some measurements
可以做些測量的
it's not fake
這不是假的事情
So he breaks up and repeats it several times
所以他分開再重複好幾次
Every time he weighs it
每一重一次他就包
Make it thinner without touching it once
沒弄一次就薄一點
at the end
弄到最後的時候
It takes a piece of Silicon
它拿一片Silicon
It's like something we use to make the bottom
等於是我們拿來做墊底的東西
put this thing on it
把這東西弄在上面
scrape it off
用刮了把它去
spread to the surface
傳到表面上去
Then if you find the thinnest layer
然後你如果找最薄的一層
The thinnest seems to be very close to transparent
最薄的好像很接近透明的
very thin very thin on top
很薄很薄放在上面
then remove
然後拿掉
There is a little bit when it is removed like this
這樣子拿掉的時候有一點點
will stick to it
就會附著在上面了
then put this thing
然後把這個東西
get an optical microscope
拿到光學顯微鏡上去
it's more complicated
這比較複雜
This family does not have
這個人家家裡沒有的
to light microscope
到光學顯微鏡
then go to
然後去找
Find an assistant for every college student in school
找每個大學生在學校助理
you can find
就可以去找
then just look for it
然後就找找找找
Here is a thin
這邊是一個很薄
Can't see clearly
看不太清楚
because it's here
因為它這邊
it seems to be transparent
它這邊好像透明
It seems that this place is opaque
好像不透明這個地方
then carefully measure
然後仔細去測量
That's one or two layers
這就是一層或兩層的
shixi is there
石墨習在那裡
So this is
所以說這個是
when this thing comes out
當這個東西出來以後
Everyone thinks I can do it right now
大家都覺得我馬上可以做出來
I'll be able to take some measurements right away
我就馬上可以做一些測量了
So everyone this is a
所以大家這是一個
It's like saying that it's a rare opportunity to say
等於是說很難得的一個機會說
you can produce these things
你可以produce這些東西
At the beginning, these two people did this because they
當初這些兩個人就是因為這樣做了以後
to measure and they speak in Double
去測量 然後他們拿Double而講
so
所以
ok now
好 那現在
Why
為什麼
This is a
這是一個
an important breakthrough
一個重要的突破
Because it seems so simple
因為這個東西好像很簡單
one by one
一個一片
one slice
一片
A membrane of a nanometer
一片奈米的一個膜
something amazing
有什麼了不起的東西
That's mainly because
那主要是因為說
in our electronics industry
在我們的電子工業裡面
everyone has heard
大家都聽到過
Selick
Selick
All our iPhones
我們的所有的拿的iPhone
everything inside the computer
所有的東西電腦裡面
now everything is
現在的東西都是
made with fine
用細做的
That's an entire industry
那是一個整個工業的
since 1948
從1948年開始
Then
然後
These transistors are
這些電晶體被
was found out
被發現出
invented
發明出來了
Then what
然後呢
we were
我們那時候
selected
選定了
The elements of drama are those of us
戲元素是我們這些
these enemies
這些為敵的
so we had
所以我們那時候有
Single Crystal is a single catty system
Single Crystal 就是一個單斤的系
principle we start mass manufacturing
原則我們開始大量製造
Then this happened
然後發生了這些
invented these commercial
發明了這些commercial
This is Pian Junking
這是Pian Junking
Some form of these transistors
這些某一種形式的電晶體
and then in the next
然後在接下來
Birth of the collective line 1958
集體線路的產生 1958 年
It was many years ago
這都很多年前的事情了
But after this collective circuit is produced in this way,
可是這個集體電路這樣產生之後
we can mass
我們可以大量的
make things more and more complicated
把事情越做越複雜
and then the features get better and better
然後這些功能就越來越好
everybody knows
大家都知道
Then around 1965
然後在大概 1965 年的時候
There was a man named Gordon Moore
有一個人叫做 Gordon Moore
He made a statement
他就提出了一個說法
That is to say, he saw
就是說他看當時
The development of the whole manufacturing industry
整個製造業的發展情形
Then he predicted
然後他就預測說
us transistors
我們這些電晶體
Or these processors will get better and better
或這些 processor 會越做越好
Then his development trend is to say
然後他的發展趨勢是說
We are on a CPU in a
我們在一個 CPU 在一個
What are those on the component called?
叫什麼元件上的那些
Number of transistors
電晶體的數目
U.S.
美國
It is estimated that it will double every two years
大概預測大概每兩年就會加倍
doubles every two years
每兩年就會加倍
So it was painted from 1971 to 2001
所以它從1971年畫到2001
This is the number of our transistors
這是我們的電晶體的數目
You take one of our internal GPUs
你拿一個我們裡頭的GPU
Inside the Central Process Unit
裡頭的Central Process Unit
The number of transistors on your
你上面的電晶體的數目
I can probably see it from behind. I can't see clearly
大概可以看到後面去看不清楚
This is Painting 4
這是Painting 4
Everyone remembers that in 2001
大家記得說2001的時候
Painting 4 probably has
Painting 4這邊大概是有
It's about 10 million here
大概是這邊是一千萬起
Thousands of transistors are on it
千萬個電晶體在上面
on the latest computer
到現在最新的電腦上
You see Painting 4
你是看到Painting 4這邊
The value of your computer has already arrived
你的電腦價值就已經到了
A, say, a billion transistors on top of
一個譬如說十億個電晶體在上面
So so many transistors have to be placed on it
所以那麼多的電晶體要擺在上面
Each must be functioning normally
每一個都要是正常的運作
your computer will be accurate
你的電腦才會算得準確
no problem
不會出任何問題
So in this situation
所以這樣子的情形下的話
You can find this thing is
你可以發現這個東西是
Getting smaller and smaller
越來越小
And what about this line
然後這個線呢
It is a
它是一個
our side is
我們這邊是
is not a Linear
並不是一個Linear
is a Lock-Rismick
是一個Lock-Rismick
It's that Lock-Scale
是那個Lock-Scale
So if this is the case, it will always be double and double
所以這樣子的話就是一直double一直double
So if this is the case
所以這樣子的話
Impossible to keep going up
不可能一直往上漲了
we are looking for
我們到要尋求
in the fine element
在細這個元素裡頭
This thing is almost at a bottleneck
這個東西幾乎已經快要到了一個瓶頸
that's there
那在
in such a development
在這樣子的發展
This is actually a history of the twentieth century
這其實是對二十世紀的一個歷史來講
is a very very very special situation
是一個非常非常非常特殊的情形
because you probably said
因為你大概說
We probably only buy computers
我們買東西大概只有買電腦
every year every two years
每過一年 每過兩年
things are getting better
東西越來越好
price did not increase
價錢沒有增加
It's outdated after a year or two
一過一兩年就已經過時了
you can imagine you buy a car
你可以想像你買車子
We are twenty or thirty years from now
我們二十年 三十年以後
Your car's speed is about the same
你車子的速度還是差不多
you never said
你從來沒有說
There is room for improvement like this
有這樣子的改進的空間
so
所以說
The result of that
那這樣帶到的結果
that is
就是說
price has been
價錢一直在
So the price of each Processor
所以說每一個Processor的價錢
Per transistor cycle
Per transistor cycle
you do the same buy the same
你做同樣的買同樣的
computer for the same money
用同樣的錢買的電腦
faster and faster
越來越快
more and more
越來越能做更多的事情
In 20, 30, 30, 40 years
在二、三十年、三、四十年下來
this is big
這個是很大
for the progress of our species
對於我們人類的進展
The development of many things is very, very
很多事情的發展是非常非常
the impact is very far-reaching
影響是非常深遠的
Although with your mobile phone
雖然隨身你的手機
Features in smartphones
智慧型手機裡頭的那些功能
is very advanced
是非常先進的
about twenty or thirty years ago
大概二、三十年前
you need a big computer
你要一個很大的電腦
one does the same thing
一個才做同樣的事情
So say in
所以說在
such a progress
這樣的一個進展
everyone will find out
大家都會發現說
this can't go on
這不可能繼續下去
So at that time everyone wanted to say
所以那時候大家想說
is having a...
有個...
This just that Law
這個剛剛那個Law
maybe...
可能會...
one day will stop
有一天會停下來
why
為什麼呢
We do this when the current motor body is loose
我們這樣當現在的電機體鬆
there will be many...
會有很多...
a lot of problems happen
很多的問題發生
Plus when you have so much stuff in there
另外當你那麼多東西都在裡面
When a lot of electrons are flowing around inside
一大堆電子在裡頭流來流去的時候
you generate a lot of heat
你會產生很多的熱量
lots of resistors
很多的電阻
Then we'll have some
然後我們會有一些裡頭
the problems in these
這些裡頭的那些問題
then it's all over that
然後它整個那個
The thickness of the Jetplasma
捷原體的那個厚度
Then we can't put something
然後我們不可能把東西
keep shrinking
一直不斷地縮小
You also shrink to the end to get to the original
你也縮到最後就是要到原始了
So in an industry like this
所以在這樣子的一個工業
Under such a big and such a big industry
這麼大的這麼大的一個產業下
everyone is thinking
大家都在想說
what to do next
下一步要怎麼辦
so in
所以在
So at this time everyone is
所以這個時候大家在
I want to ask what is an alternative
想要問說什麼是替代
tie this element
系這個元素
because we almost
因為我們幾乎
entire electronics industry
整個的電子工業
It's just one industry in one department
是只是一個系的一個工業
a lot of material
很多材料
ever been considered
曾經被考慮過
like this is a
像這種是一個
A semiconductor of the so-called III-V group
所謂的三五族的一個半導體
There are these different
有這些不同的
these elements
這些元素
that they have some good properties
那他們有一些好的性質
There is something called this Mobility
有個叫做這個Mobility
Mobility basically means
Mobility 基本上來講就是說
when you test the voltage
你試電壓的時候
how fast can your electron go
你電子能夠跑得多快
you can imagine
可以這樣想像
or its
或者是它的
its frequency
它的頻
that is to say it can make
就是說它能夠做出來的
Those are the frequencies of the components
那些是元件的頻率
That's what it uses
那可是它用這些東西
Might have some better effects
可能會有一些好一點的效果
but these things are very rail
可是這些東西都非常軌
Then there are some problems
然後有一些問題所在
The middle insulator is hard to find
中間絕緣體不太好找
at the same time
那同時呢
also thought of some
也想到過一些
other bigger
其他的更大一點的
These semiconductors of BangGap
那個BangGap的這些半導體
those like
那這些像
Even the Diamond itself
即使是Diamond本身
has also been considered
也曾經曾經被考慮過
Of course they have their benefits
那這些當然他們有他的好處
we have some
這大家有一些
like ibm
像IBM
that was 몇 years ago
那在 몇年前
made a big investment
做了很大的投資
Then decided to say that there is no way to get a good product
後來還是決定說沒有辦法得到很好的產品
There's a downside to all these things
那這些東西都有一個壞處
That is not very cheap
就是說不是很便宜
then on production
然後在生產上面
If you want to grow a good body
要長好的經體的話
it's not easy
也不是很簡單的事情
So in the entire electronics industry
所以在整個的那個電子工業界
Been trying to say we're looking for a new material
一直想要說我們要找一個新的材料
new material
新的材料
So when this graphite west thing came out
所以當這個石墨西這個東西出來的時候
Everyone became very talkative
大家變得說非常有些
think it's a big thing
覺得是一個很大的一件事情
then why
那為什麼呢
This incident started when we explored the museum in Nano
這個事情當初從奈米探館的時候
everyone can see
大家就看出來
it has a nice nature
它有一個很好的性質
This nice property means that
這個很好的性質就是說
its
它的
For example, you take a copper wire or something
譬如說你拿一個一條銅線或怎麼樣
you pass the current
你通過電流
You're going to measure its resistance later
以後你要去量它的電阻
that's usually the longer words
那通常是越長的話
The resistance will be larger
電阻會越大
Because electrons have to travel such a long route
因為電子要經過這麼長的路線
As for nanoprobes or other similar structures
那對於奈米探管或者是其他的類似的結構的話
this is an experiment
這是一個實驗
That is to say, these conduction numbers and lengths
就是說這些導電氣數跟長度
that's almost irrelevant
那幾乎是沒有關係的
is a flat one line here
是一個平的一個線在這裡
means that I increase its length
表示說我增加它長度
I don't increase its resistance
我並不會增加它的電阻
Then this is a very, very good image
那這個是一個非常非常好的一個形象
That is to say, its resistance is very small
就是說它的電阻是很小很小
it doesn't lose much heat here
它不會損失太多的熱量在這裡
The reason for this is in its electronic structure
那這個原因就是在它的電子結構裡頭
In its SP2 arrangement
在它那個SP2的排列裡面
Then there is a more advanced theory
那就有比較高深的理論
to explain it in very physical terms
去把它用很物理方面的名詞去解釋
actually go figure it out
真正去把它算出來
I will not go through those for now
那這些我就現在暫時不經過那些
Because it has something to do with some very interesting physical phenomena
因為它這個跟一些很有趣的物理現象都會扯上關係
You can see it in this article where it says
你可以看到它這個文章裡頭會說
It is notation and neutrino like particle
它是notation跟neutrino like particle
It's those high energy ones
就是那種高能裡頭的那些
Some Particles in Ratvistic
Ratvistic裡面的一些Particle
so it's in this
所以它在這個
some of it
它裡面的一些
When the mathematical structure and that describe some properties
數學結構跟那個描述一些性質的時候
It has something to do with these
跟這些都有關係
So for a physicist
所以對物理學家來講
it's an interesting material
它是一個很有趣的一個材料
Then there are some deep physics in it
那它裡頭有一些比較很深的物理
how to calculate it how to understand its nature
是怎麼去計算它怎麼去了解它的性質
What about practically?
那在實用上來講呢
It is a good electronic material
它是一個很好的電子材料
Then this time was when I was exploring the museum in Nano
那這個時候是當初在奈米探館的時候
has been discovered
就已經被發現了
That's just to say that nanometer exploration is not easy to master
那只是說奈米探館這東西不太好掌握
not working well
不太好運作
So when the two-dimensional space
所以說當二維這個空間
The one with those British scientists in 2004
2004年那些英國科學家的那個
lab found
實驗室發現了說
you can make this piece of stuff
你可以弄出這一片的東西
Like that video on YouTube I just had
像我剛剛那個YouTube上的那個錄影帶
It is convenient for everyone to make it
就方便大家都可以去把它做出來的時候
Then everyone thinks
那就大家覺得
this is a very very good trick
這是一個非常非常好的一個技巧
here in this one
在這一個這裡
I guess it's probably the only place
我大概這是大概唯一的一個地方
you can see an equation stone
你可以看到一個方程石
So this is our structure
所以說這是我們這個結構
So this thing was actually in the 1940s
所以這個東西其實在四零年代
Everyone thought of it in the 1950s
五零年代大家就已經想到過
a theorist thinks
作理論的人就想到
If there is a thing like this
如果有一個這樣的東西
what kind of nature will it have
它會有一個什麼樣的性質
At that time, I already counted some
那那個時候就已經算了一些
the nature of this
這方面的性質
this is a picture
這是一個圖
I draw here and this side is energy
我畫在這裡這邊是能量
Here it actually says something like
這邊實際上講像是
momentum is momentum
momentum就是動量
electronic one
電子的一個
Usually in any solid structure
通常在任何一個固體結構
or inside the structure
或者是結構裡面
We usually look at the so-called energy levels like this
我們通常去看這樣子所謂的能階
The special place is in this part
特別的地方是在這個部分
Because this part of its energy and its momentum
因為這個部分它的能量跟它的動量
There is a direct contrast between
之間是一個直接的對比的關係
because we are in different
因為我們在不同的
inside the usual electronics
通常的電子裡面
its
它的
Its engineering equation should look like this
它的工程方程式應該是這樣
In ordinary gene numbers, ordinary semiconductors
在普通的基因數、普通的半導體
This is actually a
這其實就是一個
Momentum P-Square
Momentum P-Square
stored energy multiplied by 2
儲以能量乘2
I think you think high school physics
我想您覺得高中物理
is the momentum squared
就是動量平方
Stored by mass multiplied by 2
儲以質量乘2的話
will get your momentum
會得到你的動能
so it's basically the same thing
所以它基本是同樣的一個東西
But if this is the case
可是這樣子的話是
such a description
這樣子的一個描述的話
is a completely different one
是完全不同的一個
a structure of electrons
電子的一個結構
in such a nature
在這樣子的性質下
so
所以說
everyone has one
大家有一個
understanding is
了解就是
it is a very special substance
它是一個非常特別的一個物質
then we are in
然後我們在
You've probably heard one
你大概聽過會說一個
a term like this
這樣子的一個term
That is to say, it looks like this
就是說它這樣子一個
A relationship of linear
linear的一個關係
will get
會得到
here will get some
在這邊會得到一些
very different electronic structure
非常不同的電子結構
so i think
所以我想
That's probably all I'm talking about here.
我這大概就只講到這邊
won't go down that
不會再往下那個
If you are interested
如果大家有興趣的話
If you are interested, we can discuss it again
有興趣的話我們可以再討論一下
its main benefit
它的主要的好處
It is the so-called Mobility that I just mentioned
就是我剛剛講到的所謂的Mobility
That is to say, after you add a voltage
就是說你加一個電壓以後
How can electrons move freely?
電子會怎麼很自由的動呢
Still bumping into some big resistors
還是會碰碰碰碰到一些很大的電阻
That is for Graphene and Smootc
那在對Graphene、Smootc來講
We usually use a Mobility like this
我們通常是用一個這樣的Mobility
something like this to represent
這樣子一個東西去表示
it is quite large
它是相當大的
Usually Silicone is
通常Silicone是
Like Graphene
像Graphene來講
This is probably more than
這大概是要多個
Many, more than 100 times
很多、100多倍
So this is a very good property
所以說這是一個非常好的一個性質
This means that
這樣子的意思就是說
When our electrons flow here
我們電子在這邊流動的時候
it's been a long time
它到經過很久
About a few microns
大概幾個micron
The micron is about 10 of -6 when it is released
micron大概是10的-6的釋放的時候
there will be a collision
才會有一個碰撞
Its Linfree Path is how long it is
它的Linfree Path就是它的多久
How long does it take to collide
走多久才會碰撞
this is very long
這個很長很長的
So this is very important for making electronic components
所以這樣子是對做電子元件是非常重要的
very very good thing
非常非常好的一件事情
so this matter
所以這個事情
Everyone has already measured such a number
大家已經量到這樣一個數字
Then I think it's a
然後都覺得這是一個
A goal worth pursuing
值得繼續追求的一個目標
Scientists all over the world are trying to find a way to say
全世界的大家科學家都在想辦法說
How do I grow the best form out
我怎麼去做長最好的一個形式出來
because we just saw that
因為我們剛剛看到說
you can be very simple
你可以很簡單
use duct tape to get something out
用膠帶去弄一些東西出來
But the pollution inside
可是裡頭到底污染
It is not mass-manufacturable
也不是可以大量製造的
The goal now is to say
現在的目標就是說
how to make a like
怎麼去做一個像
It is very big in the silicon industry
silicon工業裡面很大的
size
size
capable of mass production
能夠大量生產
so everyone
所以大家全部
many many laboratories
很多很多的實驗室
now all are chasing
現在全部在追求
This is a
這是一個
a big one
一個很大的一個
A major goal to be recognized by all
大家要公認的一個主要的目標
Now this is about last year
現在這是去年大概
in 2010
2010的時候
They can grow on metal surfaces
他們可以長在金屬表面
can grow to a
可以長到一個
probably at
大概在
you want this 0.2
你想這樣0.2
millimeter
millimeter
this is so
這是這樣
so it grows to a fairly large
所以它長到一個相當大片的
A Grapin sheet
一個Grapin sheet
There are hundreds of micron in size
有幾百個micron的size
So I'm still searching
所以現在還在追尋當中
so maybe i think in the past
所以可能我想在過去
next few years maybe
今後幾年也許
Sometimes I hear in the news that
有時候會聽到新聞中說
so-and-so laboratory
某某某個實驗室
did something
做了一個什麼什麼事情
that is likely to be with
那很可能就是跟
how do they make
他們怎麼去製造
how to produce
怎麼去生產
think of a way to
想到一個方法能夠
find a good sample
找到一個很好的樣品
There is a way to mass-produce
有個方法能夠大量製造
There are many, many ways
那有很多很多方法了
One of them is of course
其中有一個當然還是
Of course it doesn't mean to explain it.
當然不是指那交代去弄了
they can grow on a
他們可以長在一個
related to semiconductor
跟半導體有關的
像Silicon Carbide
像Silicon Carbide
How do you translate it in Chinese?
那中文怎麼翻
put on it
放在它上面
then heat
然後加熱
Then the sucker runs away
然後吸原者跑掉
the remaining carbon atom
剩下那個碳原子
so it can grow to be different
所以它可以長到不同
On the Grapin of the different layers
不同層的那個Grapin上面
that in such a long way
那在這樣子的長法
has now started
現在已經開始
got some results
有一些結果了
So this just says
所以這個只是說
results in last year
在去年的結果
Might be able to make some transistors out
大概可以做一些電晶體出來了
It's the size of 34mm
它是三成四mm的那個尺寸
probably grown to
大概已經可以長到
a lot of that
好多好多的那個
ten thousand of that
一萬個那個
Transistors are now starting to do this
電晶體現在已經開始可以這樣做到
such a point
這樣的地步
So of course there is still a long way to go
所以這以後當然路還是很長
But we slowly start
但是我們慢慢慢慢的開始
it will be like this
會有這樣子的
probably in the near future
可能在不久的將來
everyone can see say
大家可以看到說
some results came out
有一些結果出來
certainly
當然
people will ask
大家會問說
Our current computer is so good
我們現在這個電腦已經這麼好了
so convenient
這麼方便了
i do something every day
我每天我做一些
Receive some emails directly
直接收一些email
take a look online
上網看一看
I don't need that big function
我也不需要那麼那麼那麼大的功能
OK
OK
so nothing wrong
所以沒有錯
This I think probably this thing is
這個我想大概這個東西就是
some things you will need later
以後有些東西你會需要一些
compare special features
比較特殊功能
that special thing
特別特別的那個東西的話
this is still
這個還是
That is to say, common things still exist
就是說還是普遍的東西還是會存在
then this may be another development
那這可能是另外一條發展
That is to say, the development of computers with high performance and special functions
就是說發展那種高功能特殊功能的電腦
It may be necessary to find some new materials to do this
那可能要找到一些新的材料來做這方面的事情
so we'll see
所以這個我們拭目以待
maybe in the next few years
可能是今後幾年
I know several big companies like IDM or
我知道好幾個大公司像IDM或者是
What about Texas Instruments?
Texas Instruments那什麼
Some of us are heavily invested
一些大家都是大量投資
Hope to be able to not lag behind in this field
希望能夠在這個領域中不要落後
But there's still a lot of it
但這個其中還是有很多很多
scientific problems to be solved
科學上的問題要解決
Now I want to summarize
那現在我想歸納一下
The graphite west area we just talked about
我們剛剛講的那個石墨西這一片
look at the atom
看原子
It's the thinnest material we know of
它是我們現在有所知最薄的材料
because it's only one atom thick
因為它只有一個原子厚
then what about it
然後它呢
Has great Electron Mobility
有很大的Electron Mobility
Its battery movement is pretty good
它的電池的運動是相當好的
At least 100 times better than Silicone
比 Silicone 的好掉於至少100倍
Now continue to improve the material may be even better
現在繼續改進材料可能還會更好
And it's a very, very special material
同時這是一個非常非常特殊的材料
because it has other features
因為它還有其他的一些特性
This Silicone is not available
這個 Silicone 是沒有的
For example, its electrical conductivity is also very good.
譬如說它的電導電能力也是很好的
so what happened to you hot
所以你發生什麼熱
Let it go and you'll spread the word
放一下你也會傳出去
this is a strange thing
這很奇怪的事情
It's very nice to have pine silver already metalized to heat
它把屬鬆銀子已經金屬到熱性是非常好的
It puts silver 10 times better than silver
它把銀子比銀子還好10倍
so heat doesn't build up
所以熱不會累積
will spread
就會傳出去了
Then it is also a strong
然後它同時也是一個很強
very strong material
很強韌的一個材料
Because their carbon atoms follow the carbon atoms
因為它們的碳原子跟碳原子
Chemicals are strong
化學件是很強的
So it's also hard to tear it apart
所以它也很難把它扯破
Usually we know that very strong materials
通常我們知道很強韌的材料
For example, steel
譬如說鋼鐵
He will be two hundred times stronger than him
他會比他還強個兩百倍
That is, if we pull it up
就是說如果我們把它拉起來
just put so much pressure
就施多好壓力
he still won't break
他還是不會破
so he is a
所以他是一個
On the other hand, it is also a strange
另外一方面也是一個很奇怪
have very special properties
有很特殊的性質
Then this is physically and engineering
然後這是在物理上跟工程上
Compared with such considerations
比較有這樣的考量
But in chemistry
可是在化學上
We also found some very strange
大家還發現了一些很奇怪
very special news
很特別的新聞
Because it's a piece of this thing
因為它是一片一面這個東西
So we can put a lot of different
所以我們可以擺很多不同的
chemical molecule on top
化學分子在上面
then change its properties
然後改變它的性質
so many many chemists
所以很多很多化學家
or the chemistry industry are doing different research
或化學業都在做不同的研究
wish to change its nature
希望改變它的性質
take say put some different molecules
採取說把一些不同的分子
put it on top
放在上面
Adsorbed on it
吸附在上面
then change its properties
然後改變它的性質
at the same time on the optical
同時在光學上面
This is the one I want to pursue now
這是一個現在想要追求的一個
It also has some optical properties
它也有一些光學性質
we can use
我們可以用
Usually in this so-called
通常在這所謂的
The one that SpinTronics uses that electron
SpinTronics 用到那个电子的那个
Spin word spin above it has some
Spin 字旋上面它有一些
Those functions of magnetic
磁性的那些功能
It is also very likely that there are some
它也是非常有可能是有一些
The application space is inside
应用的空间在里面
So this is why there are so many papers
所以说这是为什么会有那么多的论文
Because everyone will find different places in it
因为大家会在里头找不同的地方
do things differently
做不同的事情
That many people now think of its application
那很多人现在想到它的应用
that in this thing is just in
那在这个东西只是在
This is from that YTPD
这是从那个YTPD上来
because everyone this place
因为大家这个地方
Everyone can put different things on it
每个人可以摆不同的东西上去
that can be found saying
那可以发现说
Let's say you cut it into a
譬如说你把它切成一个
ribbon thing
带状的东西
In addition there is another
另外有在另外一个
Give it another direction
另外一个方向给它一些
Confirmation is limited to
confirmation的局限到
you will find that say
你会发现说
Hey, you can change some electronic structures
哎又可以把一些电子结构改变一下
So this is called Natal Rehab
所以这是所谓的Natal Rehab
So many laboratories are doing this kind of work now
所以现在也是很多实验室在做这样的工作
Then it can do a
然后它可以做一个
molecular gas detector
molecular gas detector
You put different molecules on top
你擺了不同的分子在上面
you find it conductive
你發現它的導電
or those inductions
或者是那些感應
you can measure it
你都可以測得到
Then of course we've seen
然後當然我們已經看到
Groger's Transistor
Groger's Transistor
can already be made
已經可以做出來了
Integrate Circuit
那Integrate Circuit
Integrated circuits start slowly
機體電路先慢慢開始
You can put a lot of transistors on it
大家可以把很多的電晶體擺在上面了
Then we saw that someone wanted to use it to do
那我們看到說有人想要用它做
The function of that solar cell
那個太陽能電池的功能
Because it's something in this area
因為它這一片的東西
can make good electrodes
可以做很好的電極
Then some Bio-Device
然後有些Bio-Device
Then found out that bacteria don't like
然後發現說細菌不喜歡
This M-Pack Bacteria Stuff
這M-Pack Bacteria的東西
bacteria don't like this stuff
細菌不喜歡這個東西
So you can consider saying
所以大家可以考慮說
This can be done for applications in Bio-
這可以做在Bio-方面的應用
So after this thing comes out
所以這個東西出來以後
All scientists develop independently
大家科學家自己各自發展
everyone's imagination
大家的想像力
Then hopefully it will find that say
然後希望它能夠發現說
how things would be different
事情會有什麼的不同的情形象
can happen
可以發生
can create the one that will find various applications
可以創造出會發現各種應用的那個
right
對
good
好
Come again, I want to go back to the end
那再來我想回到最後
That is to say our original one of course
就是說我們當然原來的那個
Morse that Roll
Morse那個Roll
let's go back to that
我們再回到那個
I might go back to that picture just now
我可能回到剛剛那個圖上去
That is to say, this thing
就是說這個東西呢
keep going up
一直往上走
our e-sports
我們的那個電競體
On that CPU more and more
在那個CPU上越來越多
computers are getting faster
電腦越來越快
that's possible
那這個可能
what about this line
這條線呢
This is Silicon's line
這是Silicon的線
Maybe it's going up all the way to the end and it will definitely hit HIT
可能就是一直路上升到最後一定會HIT的
must reach this limit
一定會達到這個局限
What about before reaching this limit?
那在達到這個局限之前呢
we can imagine
我們就可以想像說
Maybe change a thread or use another material
可能換一條線或者是用別的材料
that could be the one
那可能它的那個
The whole limit might be different
整個那個限制可能會是不一樣
that's what we want to do right now
那這是我們目前想要做的事情
Then Guo Renmu put this
那郭人沐當初把這個
when making this prediction
提出這個預測的時候
He also imagined that when
他是也是想像說到時候
such a degree
這樣子的一個程度
This is a so-called Explonational Growth
這是一個所謂的Explonational Growth
But it just can't be Forever
但就是不可能是Forever
So he finally proposed in 1965 that year after
所以他最後在當年1965年提出這之後
in his 50 years
在他50年的時候
I put him in the last one
我把他放到最後一張
on his 50th anniversary
他在50週年的時候
he mentioned
他就提到說
No explanation is forever
No explanation is forever
it's impossible to go all the way up
就不可能一路漲
but
但是
Ok, Delay forever
Ok, Delay forever
Just change that forever
就把那個forever改掉了
So everyone hopes to find new materials
所以說大家希望能夠找到新的材料
be able to develop another way
能夠另外發展一條路
I think a lot this time
這次我想很多很多
Scientists in the world are now a goal to strive for
現在世界上科學家是一個努力的目標
Like I'm coming to an end today
像我今天就在一個告一個段落
Then
然後
I'll see if you have any questions
我看看大家有什麼問題
Thank you Director Zhou for your wonderful speech
謝謝周所長很精采的演講
we have a lot of time
我們有很多時間了嘛
is there anyone here who can
是不是在座有誰可以
Ask Director Zhou
請教周所長
you just mentioned that
你剛剛有提到那個
Graphite sita is ten times better than winning
石墨西他比贏好十倍
Then I will ask Director Zhou
那麼請教那個周所長以後
Is it possible that Moxi West can expect to win at all
石墨西有沒有可能完全期待贏
The second question is
那第二個問題是
The cost of graphite west and the cost of winning
石墨西的成本跟贏的成本
How much is the difference? Thank you
差距多少 謝謝
OK he's ten times better than winning
OK 他比贏好十倍
That's his thermal conductivity
那是他的導熱性質
To win has his function
對 贏有他的功能
Winning him is a very expensive thing
贏他是贏也是很貴的東西
why is it expensive
為什麼會貴呢
because he's almost he's a precious metal
因為他幾乎他是一個貴重金屬
he is not easy
他不容易
Not easy to oxidize, right?
不容易氧化 對不對
like gold
跟金子一樣
Pure gold is also not easy to oxidize
純金也很不容易氧化
Feature Stick Metal
特征棍金屬
it has its special form
它有它特殊的形式
Although the meaning of replacing the battalion is to say
雖然說取代營的意思就是說
you may be in some
你可能在某些
Let's say I need to be very thermally conductive
譬如說我需要導熱性很強
Of course we have some contacts
當然我們一些接觸
Where do you go in two years?
兩個年接什麼地方的話
Metal Has Its Benefits
金屬有金屬它的好處
it can melt with sweat
它可以汗融化了
Then glue it on like that
然後黏在上面就那樣子
What is actually a two-dimensional thing
什麼其實是一個二維的東西
So it's only partially possible
所以說只是部分可以
no way completely
沒有辦法完全
cannot completely replace
不能完全取代
because every material has
因為每個材料都有
The benefits of each material
每個材料的好處
Give plastic the benefits of plastic
給塑膠有塑膠的好處
Glass has the benefits of porcelain
玻璃有磁器的好處
So we use it for something
所以我們用它的東西
is the best place to use it
是用它最好的地方
That high thermal conductivity
那這個導熱性高
have a comparative advantage
有一個比較好處
For example, many of us
譬如說我們很多
you are in the computer
你在電腦裡面
Normally you would think this place
通常你會覺得這個地方
The CPU is very hot
CPU的地方特別熱
next to
旁邊還有
Add a fan to send the heat out
加風扇把熱送出來
sometimes you are opening to see
有時候你在打開來看
one place it has a copper shelf
有個地方它有一個銅的架子
over there for heat dissipation
在那邊散熱用的
So if you use something like graphite
所以在用石墨西這種東西的話
It's no problem to dissipate heat.
散熱它導熱出去是沒問題
so it's a benefit
所以這是個好處
so it dissipates heat quickly
所以它散熱很快
yes it will spread the heat
對 它熱會傳出去
it will spread
它會傳出去
when it works by itself
它本身運作的時候
doesn't generate a lot of heat either
也不會產生很多熱量
because it's that
因為它的那個
great mobility
mobility很大
so it doesn't say
所以它並不會說
The heat is because we have resistance
熱量是因為我們有電阻
Resistance is where electrons pass through
電阻的話就是電子走過
I'm about to collide with someone
就要跟人家碰撞一下
hit it hit it hit it
碰撞一下碰撞一下
generate a lot of heat
就產生很多熱
It has to go a long way before colliding
它這個是要走很長才會碰撞
So yes it's good here
所以是它的好處在這裡
Yes, there may be some possibilities in the future
對 以後可能還有一些可能性
Of course if we say good
當然我們如果說很好的
thermal conductivity
導熱性質的話
then design these
那再設計這些
These heavy heads these electronic components
這些重頭這些電子元件
about to be redesigned
就要重新設計了
Redesign him to take full advantage of his benefits
重新設計他可以充分利用他這個好處
Thanks
謝謝
What about the second question?
第二個問題呢
his
他的
his cost
他的成本
cost
成本
Cost is hard to say now
成本現在很難講
Because now
因為現在
us
我們
you imagine this
你想像這個
Silicone industry this industry
Silicone industry這個工業
from
從
take off in the 60s
60年代起飛
until now
到現在
40 years 40 years 50 years this
40年 40年 50年這個
decades down
幾十年下來
everything is already
所有的東西都已經
completely
完完全全的
developed
發展出來了
so
所以
For Smoji his
對Smoji而言他的
how to make the first
第一個怎麼製造
Now
現在
Is it still in a stage of scientific research
現在是在還是一個科學研究的一個階段
Because we still want to find the best way
因為我們現在還想找一個最好的方式
The cheapest way to manufacture in large quantities
最便宜的方式可以大量製造
and then made his
然後製造出來他的那個
the extent of his limit
程度啦他的限值又
not too many impurities
不要太多雜質
So this is what we just mentioned
所以這個東西就是我們剛剛提的說
Scientists almost all over the world think that
幾乎是全世界科學家都覺得
It's a very, very clear goal
這是一個非常非常清楚的一個目標
you know who can find a best way
你知道誰能夠找到一個最好的方式
He may be the next number
他可能就是下一個number而講
so he knows
所以他知道說
This is a very important topic
這是一個很重要的一個題目
Then if it can be solved
然後如果能夠解決的話
The impact on the future is very heavy
對將來的那個影響是很重很大的
So in the end how expensive he will be
所以說到底他會是多貴
or how
或是怎麼樣
now we have no idea
現在我們完全不知道
because how is this
因為這個怎麼是
Everyone is still playing
整個大家還在比賽
say who can find the best way
說誰可以找到最好的方式
So how much will it cost him?
所以這樣他的成本會多高
we don't know now
我們現在不曉得
silver is expensive
銀是很貴的
we know silver is expensive
我們知道銀是很貴的
so
所以說
So it's hard to predict what the future holds
所以這很難預測未來會是怎麼樣
For example, you go back to 20 years ago
這個譬如說你倒退回20年前
then someone tells you
然後有人告訴你說
you can hold a phone in your hand
你手上可以拿一個電話
20 years ago there were mobile phones which were very big
20年前也有行動電話是很大很大的
still on the car
還放在車子上
because of the contact
因為聯繫的那樣
So now like this little phone
所以說現在像這麼小小的電話
told you 20 years ago
20年前告訴你說
I have a call after you sign
你簽了以後有個電話
You can also access the Internet
上面還可以上網
At that time, I didn't know what the internet was
那時候還不知道什麼叫做上網
So what will happen next?
所以說後面會怎麼發展
This is difficult for us to predict
這個我們比較難預料
That's just to say that each of these research breakthroughs
那只是說這些每一次的一個研究的突破
will give us some new hope
都會給我們帶來一些新的希望
in cash
以現金來講
The gap between graphite and rock
石墨西跟岩的差距
Now look at what kind of graphene
現在看要怎麼樣的石墨西
you can make it yourself from the account
你可以自己從交代上做出來
or are you going to buy
或者是你要去買
someone can grow
有人可以長出來
There aren't many that are really on sale right now.
那現在真的在賣的也沒有太多
because everyone is developing
因為大家都在發展
Today I said I can sell you a little today
今天我說我今天可以賣你一點
There is a new method coming out tomorrow
明天有新的方法出來了
That is to say, there are constantly new
就是說不斷的有新的
Every month, you will see new papers coming out
每個月每個月就會看到有新的論文出來
i want to do this
我要這樣子做
It will take a while before we can decide who will eat it
這個還需要一段時間才能夠決定說入食誰手
or what is the best way
還是什麼樣的方式是最好的
Thanks
謝謝
Watch the news slowly, maybe in the next few years, you will see some in the news
慢慢看新聞大概今後幾年才會在新聞裡頭看到一些
Said that agricultural scientists discovered something
說農貨科學家發現了一個什麼東西
Let what is related to the real ink system
讓什麼的跟實墨系有關
There should be a lot of news about this
這個應該會有很多很多新聞產生
Thank you so much
Thank you so much
Who
哪一位
Ask Director Zhuo
請問一下卓所長
It is because of the Lanometer part
就是因為這個Lanumeter這個部分
In our natural world
在我們自然界來講
did it happen naturally
是還不是自然發生的
I mean say for example
我的意思就是說比如說
Galaxy T
Galaxy T
Then we will develop to a certain point in the future
那麼將來我們發展到某一個地步
our natural world
我們自然界
Because the industry has used a lot of Lanometer
因為工業界用了很多Lanumeter之後
There is no way for nature to consume these things that come out
自然界沒有辦法消耗這些出來的東西
Then if we prevent these phenomena
那我們如果來預防這些現象
now a subject
現在是一個課題
means sell your stuff
就是說賣你的東西
Is it harmful to the human body
對人體是不是有害
because you know small things can go through
因為你知道很小東西可以穿透
So while some people do some research
所以雖然有一些人做一些研究
that is to say, what harm will
就是說會有什麼樣的害處
That thing is not very clear now
那這個東西現在還不是很清楚
because something like
因為有些東西像
Something like that Carbon-6-6-6
有些像那個 Carbon-6-6-6
not very reactive
不是很 reactive
It is not easy to reflect with many things
就是它不是跟很多東西容易反映的
So the comparison probably won't do much harm
所以比較可能會不會造成太大的傷害
you are right
你說的沒有錯
Naturally, there are some like that nano-explorer
就自然間有一些像那個奈米探館
found out later
就後面發現說
when it heats like this
當它這樣加熱的時候
As far as everyone finds out, those who say black
就大家發現說黑黑的那些
Inside those things
探的那些東西裡頭
Maybe it was before
說不定以前就有過
It's just that people didn't find it
只是人家沒有發現到而已
But more and more man-made examples of these nanometers
不過越來越多人造的這些奈米的例子
Of course, you have to be more careful what kind of elements you look at.
當然就要比較小心你看什麼樣的元素
At least for now there will be
至少目前會有
Haven't found a big big one that hurts
還沒有發現說一個很大很大的一個傷害
But this is in the engineering school
不過這是在工學院裡頭
about environmental engineering
關於環境工程方面
This is a very important subject
這是一個非常重要的課題
That is to say, considering the problem of environmental pollution
就是說考慮到環境污染的問題
or harm to the human body
或者對人體的傷害的問題
This is something everyone is considering now
這是一個現在大家也有在考慮的
a subject among some
一些當中的一個課題
that said in nature
那說在自然界
like i said far away
就像我說的在遙遠遙遠的
There is actually that desire in my luck
心運裡頭居然有那一番求存在
it's surprising
這是很令人驚訝的事情
Maybe we've had it on Earth before
說不定我們以前地球上也有過
It's just that everyone didn't try to find it out.
只是大家沒有去把它找出來而已
so
所以說
I think a very short answer
我覺得一個很短的答案
Probably what I just said
大概就是跟剛剛說的說
This is a subject currently under study
這是一個目前在研究的一個課題
It is also an important subject
也是一個很重要的課題
What kind of harm will it do to humans?
到底是會對人類造成什麼樣的傷害
will it hurt
是不是會傷害
it's not clear yet
現在還不是很清楚
maybe for some elements
可能對某些元素來講
It is because some elements are more poisonous
它是本來有些元素就比較毒一點
If it becomes endurance
那如果變成耐力的話
when it penetrates the skin or something
那個可以穿透皮膚啊或什麼的時候
That may cause more damage
那可能就它的傷害比較大
For charcoal
那對炭來講
It compares if it doesn't work as well as others
它比較如果它跟人家不太作用的話
then it might not be that big
那它可能就不是那麼大
But this time Liu Dai said that scholars and experts should study it carefully.
不過這次劉代說學者專家去好好的把它研究出來
thank you for a very good speech
謝謝非常精彩的演講
Two questions for Chief Zhou
兩個問題請教一下周首長
the first one is very
第一個就是很
A while ago HITC Superconductor was a very, very popular topic
一陣子以前HITC Superconductor是一個非常非常熱門的題目
But then there are several technical problems
但後來有幾個技術上問題
Of course, the most important thing is that there is no way to mention three things and four temperature
當然最主要就沒有辦法提三道四溫
if say
假如說
If one day Superconductor ITC can be raised to room temperature
有一天Superconductor ITC能夠提升到室溫的話
Which one do you think is more effective than this one?
那跟您這個比你是覺得哪一個的更有效
or better
或是更好
This is the first question
這是第一個問題
The second question I want to ask is
第二個問題想請教一下就是說
Most of his people so far speak Electronics
他到目前為止大部分人講Electronics
Talk about the Golden one just now
講剛剛那個Golden的
If the Golden Model seems to be 2Dimension
那個Golden Model 如果好像都是2Dimension
Have you thought about 3Dimension
有沒有去思考到3Dimension
Use Optical and Transparent
用Optical 用Transparent這樣的話
In fact, he only needs to add a Dimension
那其實他只要增加一個Dimension
He can increase quickly
他可以很快的可以增加
thousands of times millions of times
上千倍上百萬倍
Is this another way to get around that limitation
這是不是另外一個可以打破那個限制的方法
Thanks
謝謝
OK
OK
very good question
非常好的問題
first question
第一個問題
Hitc superconducting high temperature superconducting
Hitc 超導的那個高溫超導
The benefits he wants to solve or can get
他所要解決或能夠得到的好處
not like this
跟這個不太一樣
His main thing is that he just wants to fight
他的主要是他只想打
will not say
不會說
But it is not a
可是它並不是一個
But semiconductors are not a
但半導體不是一個
make that electronic component
做那種電子元件
it can be used
它可以用來
That is to say, some parts can also be used in the middle
就是說中間也可以用到某部分
make wires what?
做導線啊什麼
But it doesn't have the structure of these semiconductors
可是它並不是有這些半導體的結構
have these good qualities
有這些好的性質
This is what we need to make a
這是我們需要製造一個
Materials used to make a computer like this
做一個電腦這樣子用的材料
That high temperature superconductor is now
那高溫超導現在
That is to say, there are some technical problems
就是說有些技術上的問題
after it reaches a certain stage
它到了某個階段以後
just stop there
就停在那裡
the temperature won't go up
溫度就上不去了
Of course this means
當然這個東西就是說
one suddenly has a breakthrough
一個突然有一個突破
then stop there
然後就停在那邊
many many years
很多很多很多年
Everyone can't find a way to break it
大家想找不到破解的方法
This will say to wait for the next wave
這個就會說要等下一波
Now a lot of people are finding new material
現在很多人都在找到新材料
The temperature is not that high
什麼這個溫度都沒有那麼高
But the more we learn about this substance
不過我們對這個物質的了解越多
We know better which direction to look for
我們就比較知道從哪個方向再去找
So there is no basis for this
所以跟這個是沒有底處的
The two problems solved are different
兩個解決的問題是不一樣的
The two solutions are not the same
兩個解決問題是不一樣的
that physically speaking
那在物理上來講
they are very
他們都是很
Both are a very challenging
兩個都是一個很去挑戰性的
one of those subjects
一個那些課題
That is, if someone can figure it out
就是說如果有人能夠解出來的話
This is
這是
That is to say, a very big contribution
就是說很大很大的貢獻
That
那
Just the second question
剛剛第二個問題
so far
說到目前為止
to this 2 reps
到這個2 個代表
2 reps
2 個代表
right
對
exist
在
before this
在這個之前
while everyone is discussing that
在大家討論那個
When Morse Law
Morse Law的時候
there is a direction
那有一個方向就是
The transistor that walks in 3D
走3D的那個 transistor
was that time
是那個時候曾經
And there are still some people
而且現在還是有一些人
Continue to pursue making it 3D
再繼續追求把它弄成3D
make it flat
弄成平面那樣子
inside too
裡頭也是
encountered some difficulties
碰到一些困難
That is according to the material
那是隨從材料上來講
You just mentioned another
那您剛剛提到另外一個
That is to say, from the optical way
就是說從 optical 光學上的方式
to interact with him
去跟他 interact
That's the direction everyone's been thinking about for many years.
那這個方向是大家想很多年
Because in the silicon base
因為在 silicon base 的時候
What we call optical electronics
我們所謂的 optical electronics
we hope to have some
我們希望有一些
Silicon can follow
silicon 能夠跟
Those laser beams or some optical ones
那些 laser beam 或什麼光學那些
some coupling
有些 coupling
which can then be put together
然後可以把它合在一起
Not just conductive electronics come out
不只是導電的 electronics 出來
Then follow this outside optical
然後跟這個外頭的 optical
The probes are somewhat associated
的 probe 是有些關聯的
so that was a very
所以那是一個很
That is to say, a big subject
就是說很大的一個課題
many people are chasing
很多人在追求
It's just that at that time
只不過那個時候是
silicon with
silicon 跟
Because it is it does not absorb light very well
因為它是它對光的吸收性不是很好
Because it is the so-called indirect gap
因為它是所謂間接的 indirect gap
Its direct gap is relatively large
它的直接的 gap 是比較大
its absorbing light
它的吸收光線
this or that
這個大概那個
It means about three or four ED
意思要到大概三四個 ED
will have a lot of absorption
才會有大量的吸收
So that's a really big specific
所以那是一個非常大的特定
That is how to follow
就是說怎麼去跟把
The Silicone Base Electronics
這個 Silicone Base Electronics
with some of these Optical
跟這些 Optical 的一些東西
can be combined
能夠結合在一起
This is many, many, many years of hard work
這個很多很多很多年的努力
not yet fully achieved
還沒有完全能夠達到
So for Silicone
所以對 Silicone 來講
This aspect is relatively weak
這方面是比較弱的
Of course, if you change to other materials
那當然如果換了別的材料的話
maybe there is another possibility
也許有另外的可能性
This can have another
這個可以有另外的
Follow Optics and Electronics
跟把 Optics 跟 Electronics
can have a better combination
可以有更好的結合
So this is also in these semiconductor industries
所以這也是在這些半導體工業上
Some problems that everyone has been trying to solve
大家一直想要解決的一些問題
It is also the direction of development
也是一直的發展方向
It's just that there are no good results yet.
只是還沒有很好的結果出來而已
total maintenance
總維持
this is
這是啊
i want to talk
我想來講一下
has great usage
有很大的用法
i think it's ok
我想也可以
i think we can
我想我們可以
think about it
考慮一下
we need to talk to us
我們需要跟我們討論
of this object
的這個對象
Need to consult with us
需要和我們請教
Congratulations
恭喜
That is to say before Bucky Bull was
就是說之前在Bucky Bull就是
When carbon 60 came out
碳60的出來的時候
In fact, he had many different applications at the beginning.
其實他當初也是有很多不同的應用
But it doesn't seem to have seen anything yet
但似乎現在還沒有看到有什麼
practical application in life
實際應用在生活上的
I don't know if he was later
那不知道是他後來是
where did one meet him
在哪裡有遇到他的一個
the solution of development
就是發展的平解
That's compared to Graphite Creek now
那跟現在石墨溪相比
Is there any place for reference?
那有沒有什麼可以對照參考的地方
Thanks
謝謝
OK, the original carbon 60 because it is one by one
OK 原來碳60因為它是一顆一顆的
So if you want to use
所以你要用的話
I want you to find a way to get to the area
是要你要有個辦法去一顆顆區
be able to use it to do something
能夠去拿來做一些事情
and put it together or do
然後把它擺在一起或者是做
OK Carbon 60 over there
OK 碳60那邊
In fact, it will be discharged into a solid carbon 60
其實它會排起來變成一個固態的碳60
Each unit is carbon 60
每一個單位是碳60
Then there are some nice properties in that
然後在那方面有一些很好的性質
you can talk to another one
你可以再跟別的那個
Echoline Metals to put in
Echoline Metals去擺進去
make some new some
製造一些新的一些
image of object
物體的像
But the real use
可是真正的拿來用
That is to say, one by one
就是說它一顆一顆
how are you going
你要怎麼去
how do you grab one to do something
你怎麼去抓一顆來做一做事情
put it back
再把放回去
This thing is more difficult
這個事情是比較難的事情
That graphite west side
那石墨西這邊
Everyone will feel a little hopeful
大家會比較覺得有點希望的是說
wish it was such a large piece of long
希望它是這樣一大片的長
grow out of the bottom
從底下那樣長出來
Then a large piece of it is produced in large quantities
然後一大片很大量製造
Then use some more from above
然後再從上面用一些
we have those now
我們現在有那些
Lysograph's method to cut
Lysograph的方法去切啦
or make those three mouthfuls
或製造那些三口
it's easier this way
這樣子比較容易
easier to make things
比較容易去把東西做成
the shape you want
你想要的形狀
or whatever you want
或者你想要的那個東西
because of the carbon talc stuff
因為碳溜石的東西
You said you were going to grab one
你說你要把一顆抓起來
how do you catch
你怎麼抓
such a small thing
那麼小的東西
there's no way you can grab it with anything
你沒有辦法用任何東西去抓
or to adsorb
或者去吸附
or you put it
或者你把它
At best, stick it to the surface
頂多去把它吸附在表面上
to make some control changes
去做一些控制改變
Like that, so the above is a bit higher in terms of difficulty.
那樣子 所以上面是比較難度上比較高一點
So if you really go
所以說如果真正上
Is there really any good application for Greedy Stone?
貪溜石是不是有真正什麼很好的應用
that might be in science
那可能在科學上有
But it doesn't seem to say that it is made into a product
可是好像沒有說做成一個產品
It is a product of Tanyoushi.
就是貪溜石的一個產品出來
i don't know if
我不知道是不是
I'm not entirely aware of recent developments
我並不是完全很清楚最近的發展情形
So I can't talk about this place
所以這地方我不能講
That's it
就是了
At that time, Moxi was mainly because he combined the previous
那時茉希主要是他結合了以前
everyone on this surface
大家對於這個表面
The semiconductor industry is doing this on the surface
那個半導體工業在做這種表面上
how to grow film
怎麼去長薄膜
How to do these layer by layer
怎麼去做這些一層一層擺上去
There is a lot of experience in this area
這方面是有很多很多的經驗
So his two-dimensional thing
所以他這個二維的東西
He can be more easily controlled
他就可以比較容易去控制
easy to set it up
容易去把它架起來
then become something
然後變成什麼東西
Layer Shelf or Shera
一層一層的架或是薛拉
Or design some other structure
或者是設計一些其他的那個結構
it's easier stuff
這是比較容易的東西
Now the most important thing is to say
那現在最主要的地方還是說
how can you grow well
你怎麼能夠去長很好的
and then be able to control it
然後能夠控制它
can then be mass-produced
然後能夠大量生產
then also very cheap
然後也很便宜
It's not that there are only a few places where it can grow
不是說只有幾個地方可以長
OK and then when it's over
OK 然後完了以後
you can understand its nature
你可以了解它的性質
Then redesign what kind of circuit you want
然後重新設計你要什麼樣的電路
OK, the design
OK 那這個設計上
Maybe it's not the same as before
可能就跟以前的又不太一樣
Because of its electronic nature
因為它這個電子性質
The electronic structure is different
電子結構是不一樣的
ok so then what to do
OK 所以然後怎麼去
When it is possible to make a transistor
可能做電晶體的時候
you put those oxides on it
你上面放那些氧化物
or how are you going to do your
或者是你要怎麼去做你的
get your electricity
弄你的電
Other different types of transistors
其他不同形式的電晶體
So it still needs some
所以這方面還是需要一些
development over time
一些時間的發展
So the Norval value of this physics means
那所以說這個物理的Norval講值是說
We seem to have a
我們好像現在有一條
There is a direction like this
有一個方向這樣子
that can really make something
那真正能夠做出東西來
still take a while
還是需要一段時間
not so fast
不是那麼快的
So this thing is
所以這個事情是
Just to say that now I seem to see a
只是說現在好像看到一個
Seems like a pretty promising thing
好像蠻有希望的一個東西
At least after trying many, many materials in the past
至少在過去試了很多很多的材料之後
we may see there is a hope
我們可能看到有一個希望
Well, these are like a lot of US military
那這些像很多美國軍方
invested a lot of money
投入了一些很多的經費
that's what this development says
那就是這種發展的話
It is the kind of High-end is a special function
就是那種High-end就是特殊功能
Then some special electronic components
然後特殊的一些電子元件
no you probably wouldn't say
不是你大概不會說
bring this price down so low
把這個價錢會降到那麼低
Because we are so computerized now
因為我們現在這個這麼電腦
it's pretty cheap now
現在是相當便宜
also very very very
也很有非常非常的
Very powerful thing
很powerful的東西了
So the words of the general public
所以這個普羅大眾的話
still the one that lasts so long
還是會這麼久的那個
Silicon inter-suit will not disappear completely
Silicon的inter-suit是不會完全消失的
that just means we have another chance
那只是說我們有另外的機會
go find something better
去找更好的東西
Thanks
謝謝
Two questions. One is that the director just mentioned that
兩個問題 一個是剛剛所長有提到說
There are three types of graphite, one is spherical, the other is tube and the other is flat
石墨他有三種型 一個是球的 一個是管的 一個是平面的
I would like to ask some of their physical properties in these three states
我想請問在這三種狀態下他們的一些物理特性
For example, if I have a bunch, you don't have carbon balls to put together
譬如說如果我有一堆那你沒碳球放在一起
Then I use light, is it with a bunch of carbon tubes?
那我用光照是不是跟一堆碳管的
With lighting he has a different sheen or something
用光照他有不同的光澤還是什麼的之類的
and their properties, for example, in the six bodies
還有他們的譬如說在六體中的特性
Or is there any difference in physical properties such as conductive poison?
或是導電毒之類的物理特性有沒有一樣
Then there is the second question
然後還有第二個問題
That is, Norbell said that they used tape to layer graphite layer by layer.
就是Norbell講他們是用膠帶把石墨一層一層分層的
But when we were experimenting
可是我們在做實驗的時候
We must control every thickness of him very precisely
我們必須要很精準的控制他的每一個厚度
How to control the thickness of each layer in the laboratory
那在實驗室的時候是大概怎樣去做到說控制他每一層的厚度
Thanks
謝謝
OK first question
OK 第一個問題
He's exploring the pavilion or the ball or the flat graphite
他在探館或是球或者是平面石墨些的
Its electronic structure is different
它的電子結構是不一樣的
For example, when graphite is a piece, it will reverse electricity
譬如說石墨一片的時候它會倒電
Then if the carbon tube
然後如果碳管的話
Some carbon tubes are semiconductors
有的碳管它是半導體
Some carbon tubes are metallic
有的碳管是有金屬性
That is, their resistance is relatively small
就是它們的電阻比較小
depending on its direction
照它的方向而定
So that aspect can
所以那個方面可以
Maybe it can be adjusted
也許是說可以調
Or you can tune different carbon tubes
或者說你可以調不同的碳管
jump out that measure up
跳出來那個測量起來
may be different
都可能都不一樣
The energy level of the ball
那球的話它的能階裡頭
That is to say, there is a gap
就是說是有一個 gap
that is to say itself
就是說它本身
that is to say there is a
就是說有一個
energy gap on top
energy gap 在上面
So it's big
所以它的才算滿大的
so that
所以那個
So its properties are different
所以它的性質是不同的
nature is different
性質是不同的
That
那
The second question just now is
剛剛那個第二個問題是
thickness
厚度
How do you say to control it
你說怎麼去控制它的
OK, yes
OK,對
You tell me two... actually there is no way to control
你交代兩...其實沒有辦法控制
what to do is say
當做的事情就是說
Later, after many experimenters did this,
後來很多實驗師這樣做了以後
I made a lot of them
就弄了一大堆出來
Then go to the Wangxue Well Weijing to find
然後到那個望雪井維境下面去找
I see this seems to be two layers
我看看這個好像是兩層
There seems to be a layer
這邊好像是一層
you go find students
你找學生去
you are in a hurry to plan a lot of time
你就很急劃很多時間
Just look for it bit by bit for a month
就是一個月一點一點一點去找
Look where it says it's a layer
你看找到哪裡說這是一層的
I'm doing an experiment here
我就在這邊做實驗
so it's totally out of control
所以它是完全不能控制
what did you do
你做到什麼
look for what you see
你看到什麼就找
Maybe you can't find this piece
就許這一片你都找不到
layer by layer that never
一片一層那從來
If this is expected, you can find it
那這預計好的話你可以就找到
If you find it, you can measure it.
找到的話你就可以去做測量了
So that's pretty much out of control
所以那個是幾乎不能控制的
After that, the more advanced method now
那以後呢現在比較先進的辦法
That is to say, if you can grow
就是說你如果可以長的話
You can adjust the situation in the laboratory
你就可以調實驗室的那個情形
one or two layers
長一層或長兩層
but only later
但是以後才能控制
So it was just a
所以當初只是一個
a very simple way
一個很簡單的方式
there are some samples you can take some measurements
有一些樣品你可以做一些測量
Then after taking measurements, it was found that
然後做了測量以後發現
this seems
這個好像
This is of good nature
這個性質滿好的
the whole can repeat
那整個的能夠重複
These things don't hit the nail on the head every time
這些東西不是每次百發百中
that's mainly for you
那主要是為你說
Many, many labs can do the same thing
很多很多實驗室都可以做到同樣的事情
Those measurements that learn a lot can be repeated
那學著很多的那些測量都可以被重複
Then everyone will believe
那大家就相信說
this thing should be right
這個東西是應該是對的
is such confidence
是這樣子的信心
i want to ask two questions
我想請問兩個問題
It's the first Smosh
就是第一個那個史莫希
if you pull him a little bit
如果稍微把他拉一下扯一下
Then some of his physical properties will change a lot
那他一些物理特性會變化很大
The second question is
那第二個問題是
Why is the Tan-60 called Lingwei structure?
那個Tan-60為什麼要叫靈微結構
does he have a story
他有什麼故事嗎
if you pull
你拉一下的話
His electronic structure will change
他的那個電子結構就會改變了
That's just saying someone weighed it down
那只是說有人把稱稱稱下
Then his electronic structure
然後他的那些電子結構
There may be a small one that can GaP will appear
可能會小小的一個能GaP會出現
Of course it would take a lot of changes
那當然要稱多改變
Only then will he change his atom-to-atom script
才會改變他的那個原子跟原子的劇本
Is someone trying to say someone took some measurements
是有人在嘗試說有人做一些測量
Then do some calculations say
然後做一些計算說
How much force is needed to make the spicy hot
把辣要辣多少要多少力
what happens to it after it's hot
辣了以後它會發生什麼情況
So this is another thing that can be tuned
所以這是另外一個可以調的東西
So if you want to change its nature
所以你如果想要把它的性質改變一下的話
This is a mechanical method
這個就算 mechanical 機械型的一個方法
can be changed
是可以改變的
The second question is why it is called Lingwei
第二問題為什麼它叫靈微
i was from behind
我那是從後面
For example, our three-dimensional space
譬如說我們這個三維空間
If you have a direction take it away
你如果有一個方向拿掉
let it not let it confine you
讓它不能讓它侷限下來的話
We become two-dimensional actions
我們變成二維的動作
Like a face, this is two-dimensional
像一個面 這樣就是二維
It can move in two directions
它有兩個方向可以動
that becomes a line again
那變成再變成一個線
If this is the case, you actually need to snuggle because it
這樣子的話其實要依偎是因為它
This direction is completely free to move
這個方向是完全自由的可以動
Then we don't consider the other side
那另外這邊我們就不考慮了
it won't come out
它出不來了
That said, get it down like this
那說這樣子弄下來
What do you call one when you search for me?
你把一個那你探求我叫怎麼講
In other words, this is called Lingwei
還就是說這樣叫做靈微
Because I can't move in every direction
因為每個方向都動不了
this is just a description
這只是一個描述而已
It's not that what that spirit means
並不是說那麼靈代表什麼意思
Just saying that every direction is restricted
只是說每個方向都受到限制
All directions are restricted
所有的方向受到限制
so there's nothing left
所以沒有東西剩下來了
There is no such degree of freedom left
沒有那個自由度剩下來了
So there was a speech like this
所以有次這樣子的講法
It's not that
其實不是那個
so
這樣
sorry
對不起
because I'm not an undergraduate
因為我不是本科的
i want to ask
我想請教一下就是說
Since the previous ratio is also graphite
既然前比也是石墨
Then that graphite west is graphite
然後那個石墨西是石墨
so i heard your speech till now
所以我聽說到您的演講到現在
it feels like saying
感覺上好像說
graphite west so so good
石墨西所以那麼好
so precious
那麼貴重
simply because it can be a very thin layer
完全是因為它可以很薄的一層
big piece
很大一片
So our front ratio is many, many
所以我們的前比是很多很多
Broken graphite west piled together
破掉的石墨西堆在一起
OK
OK
It's not broken, it's a very regular arrangement
不是破掉的是很規則的排列
right
對
you
你
In fact, if you spend so much together
其實你如果那麼多成本在一起
it will automatically
它會自動的
line up because it is the lowest energy
排好,因為它是能量最低的
That graphite is what we go to the heart of thousands of miles
那石墨,就是我們到千里心裡面
The distance between each layer
它每一層跟一層的距離
Probably, this is less than one
大概是,這就是不到一個
Is a few of the collar three Answeron
是領的幾個三個Answeron
That's 0.3 nanometers
就是0.3個奈米
That means, you take one
那意思就是說,你拿一個
then it lined up well
那它排得滿好的
Sometimes the direction is a little bit wrong, it doesn't matter
那有時候方向會錯一點,沒有關係
But it's layer by layer, well piled up
不過它是一層一層,堆得滿好的
not to say that standard
不是說那麼標準說
Perfect like this, but roughly
Perfect這樣,可是大致上
this direction, this is
這個方向,這個是
Do it perpendicular to this, there is no problem
做跟這個垂直,這是沒有問題的
So what about its permutation?
所以它的那個排列呢
you can imagine saying
你可以想像說
that millimeter
那一個millimeter
Do you know how much a millimeter is
你知道一個millimeter是多少
It has about 3 million layers
它裡頭大概300萬層
inside
在裡面
so so well lined up
所以,所以排得很好
So, usually you take a piece
所以,通常你拿來一塊
Take the heart of thousands of miles down, it's a big piece, a lot of piles
千里心拿下來,到一大塊,一大堆了
didn't split it
沒有把它分出來
because
因為
Why did you say it was made this time?
這次為什麼說當初做出來大家覺得
This is a pretty good situation
這個是相當好的一個情形
Everyone wants to say take it apart
大家都想說把它分開
It's not that I can't think of a good way to separate it
那一直不是想不到一個很好的方法把它分開
Now there are still some chemical ways to separate it
那現在還有一些化學上的方法可以把它分開
That is to say, for example, if you bring graphite
就是說譬如說你把石墨拿來
you put some other molecules in between
你中間去放一些其他的分子
Or nourish it
要不然養化啦
Or put those things in OH to fill it up
或者是放到OH那些東西去把它填充
then it swells
然後它就脹開了
Yes, expand it and put it in agriculture
對 脹開了你放到農業裡頭去
It strips off every layer and every layer
它就每一層每一層就脫裸了
So this is also a method
所以這也是一個方法
chemical method
就是化學的方法
Because I still don't understand
因為我還是不懂啊
so ask
所以請教一下
Since there are many layers
那既然很多層的話
tell me if i ask a stupid question
那我如果問的問題很愚蠢的告訴我
That is to say, it is layer by layer in nature
就是說那它一層一層在自然界
Is there no way to say their
難道沒有方法說它們的
the edge of each layer
每一層每一層的邊緣
Is there any way to connect them
可以有什麼方法讓它們接起來
Because if we can find such a method
因為如果能夠找到這樣的方法
not that they are cluttered inside the pencil
不是說它們亂堆在鉛筆裡面
we just break it up
我們只要把它打散
Then each piece is connected
然後每一個小片接起來
that's what we want
就是我們要的東西
so the problem is heavy
所以問題很沉
But the other is to say
但是另外一個就是說
Since there are diamonds in nature
自然界既然有鑽石
Diamonds are also hard to make
鑽石也很難做
Will there be graphite series in nature?
自然界會不會也有石墨系
Although we humans find it difficult to do
雖然我們人類覺得很難做
If nature had a way of forming it like this
如果自然界有這樣形成它的方法
maybe find out
也許找出來就好
we don't have to think
我們不用自己想
right
對
OK, there are graphite series in nature
OK 自然界有石墨系
Just say two pieces together
只要說兩片在一起
it will come together
它就會合在一起了
because it usually interacts
因為它平常會有相互作用
Unless you have a layer of graphite
除非你一層石墨系
you are on a surface
你就在一個表面上
just stand over there other stuff
就站在那邊其他東西
don't touch it
不要去碰它
or how does it find
或者它怎麼去找
Now I mean, everyone think of a way to say
現在就是說大家想辦法說
grow it in the lab
在實驗室把它長出來
it's heating or something
就是加熱啦或者什麼樣的
it grows naturally
它自然長出一層來
This is what everyone wants now
這現在是大家想要得到的話
if nature
如果說自然界
It has been achieved that it can be naturally developed into a layer
已經做到能夠自然展成一層
Then we humans can find this method
那我們人類可以把它找到這個方法
to develop it naturally into a layer
去把它自然展成 長成一層
Because if many layers collide
因為如果很多層碰在一起以後
become graphite
變成石墨
Graphite is useless.
石墨這個東西就沒有什麼用了
because it works later
因為它的作用以後
it becomes it is a metal
它變成它是一個 metal
Then it just says less
然後它就是說少掉
some nice features
一些很好的功能
When you get to the first floor
你要到一層了以後
some other features
那一些其他的一些特性
will run out
就會跑出來了
After interaction
互相作用以後
will offset these things
會把這些東西抵消掉
sorry
對不起
i'll waste a little more time
我再浪費一點時間
but you just said
可是您剛有說
A pencil is many small flakes of graphite
鉛筆是很多小片小片的石墨西
'cause they suck together
因為他們對在一起就變得很糟糕
But every little piece
可是每一個小片
It will always have a beginning from graphite to a small piece
它總會有個開始從石墨變成一個小片
but how do you pick out
可是你怎麼挑出來
you can't your fingers so single
你不能你手指這麼單
How would you pick out
怎麼會把挑出來
you have to have a very thin
你要有一個很細
something the size of a round paper
一個圓紙大小的東西
clip paper to clip it out
夾紙去把它夾出來
this is something we didn't do
這是我們沒有做到的事情
there is no way you have a round paper
你沒有辦法有一個圓紙
The size of the paper clip to pick out this layer
大小的夾紙把這一層的挑出來
if it can be done
如果能夠做到的話
Just pick that layer out
就直接把那一層就挑出來了
IPN seems to have AtomTrees
IPN好像有AtomTrees
Then I remember that in biochemistry
然後那個我記得生化裡面
Seems like a technology called LaserTrees
好像一種技術叫做LaserTrees
There is no way to pull a person like this
這一種都沒有辦法去拉一個人
that is to say already
就是說已經
achieve a small degree of graphite west
達到一個小小程度的石墨西
come out piece by piece
一片一片出來
If you push the trash
對 垃圾推著的話
It is a
它是一個
it can move a large molecule
它可以動一個大分子
The space is still quite large
空間還是算滿大的
Graphite is an atom
石墨西是一個原子
So it could have the one with thousands of atoms
所以它可能有幾千個原子的那個
that thing it can control it
那個東西它可以去控制它
push it move it
推著它把它去動它
There is still a difference in scale
對 尺度還是有差
because
因為
There is still a difference in scale, the one in nanometers
尺度還是有差是奈米的那個
you might imagine
你可能想像到
like nanometer
像奈米探館的話
Now it's what everyone says is the sharpest thing
現在是大家說是最尖的東西
Because a small such a small tube
因為一個小小這麼小的一個管子
That head is very sharp
那個頭的話就是很尖
so you use it for some other application
所以你才用它去做一些其他的應用
The so-called pointed one is its
那所謂尖的就是它的那個
That circle is about a few nanometers
那個圓周大概是幾個奈米
is in the nanometer range
是奈米範圍
So presumably things will never be smaller than a nanometer again.
所以大概東西再也不會再小於奈米了
Because smaller than nanometer
因為小於奈米以後
you are about to enter the atom
你就要進入原子內
the size of an atom
跟原子的大小
is the distance between atoms
就是原子跟原子的距離
like this
像這個
On the graphite side or in the graphite system
石墨那邊或者是石墨系裡頭
The distance between judgment and detection is 0.14 difficulty
判跟探之間的距離是0.14的難度
That's probably the smallest distance
那大概就是最小的一個距離
right now we
我們現在
if you go again
你再過去的話
It's probably going to go into that thing in the yard box.
就可能要進到院子盒裡面的那個東西了
So it's chemical
所以說是化學件
We probably only had a few Ansejangs in mind
我們大概只考慮到幾個安斯庄
on this
在這上
There are plans mentioned in this major
這個專業裡面有提到的計畫
That is, the production of the West Rock Line has reached its physical limit.
就是西岩線的生產已經到了物理極限
The so-called physical limit
那所謂到了物理極限
that is
就是說
How long will it take you and us to reach that limit now
你我們現在還要多久時間才達到那個極限
or we
或者說我們
almost to the limit
快到這個極限了
But it is very difficult to reach this limit
但是要達到這個極限的難度很高
that could be a long time
那可能還要一段很長的時間
Then everyone has a lot of spirituality
那大家的精神性也很多
Then we look forward to having new materials to look forward to
那我們充滿期待有新的材料來期待
ok my so-called limit
ok 我的所謂的極限
That is to say, you have a CPU
就是說你一個CPU
How many legendary stones can be placed on the upper right
右上能放多少個傳奇石
In the end let them now be two little
到最後讓他們現在已經是兩個小
One foot is very close
一尺很近很近了
different in the middle
中間要不同的
Like we put some Oxide MRT
像我們放一些Oxide捷運體
Yes, that's already very, very thin
對,那都已經很薄很薄了
the limit is
極限就是說
you can't
你那個不可能
You are about a few percent thinner
你大概要薄到幾成
After a few percent of the round paper
幾成那個圓紙以後
you probably won't be able to go down
你大概就不能再下去
further down it will touch
再下去它就會接觸
will affect each other
彼此就會影響
so say something
所以說一個東西
current design
現在的設計
to the current design
給目前的設計方式
Then they probably in a certain situation
那他們大概在某個情形下
no longer possible
就不可能再
we can't put these things
我們不可能把這些東西
further increase
再增加下去了
that number for example
那那個數字譬如說
The current situation in 2010 now
現在2010的目前的狀況
maybe every one of you
可能你每一個
When each transistor operates
每一個電晶體運作的時候
what a nice electron
多好的電子
what a current
多好電流
maybe it's time to say
可能就是已經到了說
A dozen or twenty electrons went to operate
十幾二十個電子去operate了
so everything will come to an end
所以東西都會到最後
go down like discreet
discreet的那樣子下去
I say this because the way it's currently designed
我是這樣講是說因為照目前的設計的方式
The way everyone built the base to make it
大家基底建入的做出來的方式
The purpose of finding new materials is to say
那找新的材料的目的就是說
If the new material has better properties
如果新的材料有好一點的性質
If it is more powerful
它的功能比較更強的話
then we can say
那我們可以說
Don't go as small as that will achieve the same function
不要到那樣小的會達到同樣的功能
That means doing it in another way.
那這是說從另外一條路去做這樣子
Then everyone's ballistic body over there
那大家都這個彈道體那邊
Everyone in the industry probably has a different view
工業界大概每個人有不同的說法
that is to say you till now
就是說你到你現在
We now have a new CP coming out every year
我們現在是每年都有新的CP就出來
how long then
那再過多久
This is what is said in the past
這個現通過去的話就是說
about ten or fifteen years
大概在個十年十五年
That has already reached the complete limit of physics.
那個就已經到了完完全全的那個物理的極限了
The limit means that two things will meet together and cannot
極限的意思就是說兩個東西會碰到一起不能夠
multiple
多支
how much can you say
能夠說到多少
You have to have something to do with him
你要跟他幾成電子有關係
How many atoms are related
幾成原子有關係
That's under several tens of atoms
那在幾成原子下
He is still a semiconductor
他還是個半導體
Or he still has a Primarch
或是他還是有決原體
This is a space for discussion
這些都是一個可以討論的空間
i mean that part
我指的是那個部分
i think today was a really good talk
我想今天是一個非常精彩的演講
Many friends participated
參與的朋友也非常的多
we learned a lot of new things
我們學到非常多新的東西
I'm an amateur at this
我個人對這個是外行
So I have nothing to contribute
所以我也沒什麼可貢獻
But 20 years ago there was a cartoon
不過20年前有個漫畫
It is said that the fastest speed for human beings to send letters in the future
說人類將來送信最快的速度
The picture above is delivered by helicopter to the door of the American cargo
上面畫是用直升機送到美貨門口
did not expect
沒想到
Then ran out an E-mail out
後來跑出一個E-mail出來
Therefore, as the director said just now,
所以成如剛才做所長所講
how to develop in the future
將來要怎麼發展
we do not know
我們不知道
we will wait and see
我們拭目以待
ok we thank you zhou
好 我們謝謝周